<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The foot out of the snare with a detection of sundry late practices and impostures of the priests and Iesuits in England. VVhereunto is added a catalogue of such bookes as in this authors knowledge haue been vented within two yeeres last past in London, by the priests and their agents. By Iohn Gee, Master of Arts, of Exon-Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Gee, John, 1596-1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 194 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01576</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11701</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103001</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838760</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838760</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3148</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01576)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3148)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1066:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The foot out of the snare with a detection of sundry late practices and impostures of the priests and Iesuits in England. VVhereunto is added a catalogue of such bookes as in this authors knowledge haue been vented within two yeeres last past in London, by the priests and their agents. By Iohn Gee, Master of Arts, of Exon-Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Gee, John, 1596-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 99, [9] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. L[ownes] for Robert Milbourne, and are to bee sold at his shop at the great south doore of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliography.</note>
                  <note>Text ends on P4r. Variant: text has been extended and runs onto P4v.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  Great Britain --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3148:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3148:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Foot out of the Snare: WITH A DETECTION OF SVNDRY LATE
practices and Impoſtures of the Prieſts and Ieſuits in <hi>England.</hi>
Whereunto is added a Catalogue of ſuch bookes as in this Authors knowledge
haue been vented within two yeeres laſt paſt in London, by the Prieſts
and their Agents.</p>
            <p>By IOHN GEE, Maſter of Arts, of <hi>Exon</hi>-Colledge in
OXFORD.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by <hi>H. L.</hi> for <hi>Robert
Milbourne,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his ſhop at the great South doore of
Pauls, 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3148:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3148:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God, the Lord Arch-Biſhop of
Canterbury his Grace, and to the reſt of the Reuerend Lords Spirituall, and
the right honourable the Lords Temporal, as alſo to the moſt Worthy and
Religious Knights and Burgeſſes of the houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, all now
aſſembled in this happy Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; I. G. an vnworthy Miniſter of the
Church, preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to dedicate this euidence of his repentance, and
declaration of his beſt endeuours for the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the ſafetie of a <hi>Ship,</hi> to haue good
<hi>Pilots;</hi> the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of a <hi>Palace,</hi> to haue ſure
<hi>Pillars;</hi> the <hi>ſecuritie</hi> of the <hi>bodie,</hi> to haue
<hi>cleare eyes;</hi> and ſafe-guard of <hi>ſheepe,</hi> to haue vigilant
<hi>Shepheards:</hi> So it is the<pb facs="tcp:3148:3"/>
               <hi>ſafety</hi> of a
<hi>Countrey,</hi> and <hi>ſafegard</hi> of a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> to haue many
wiſe and watchfull <hi>Counſellors.</hi> Wee neuer had greater reaſon to
bleſſe GOD, then in contemplation of the preſent time, in the perfect
viſion of ſo many principall <hi>Planets</hi> now met together in happy
<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction:</hi> ſuch a <hi>King,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Prince,</hi> ſuch
<hi>Honourable Senators,</hi> ſuch <hi>Aſsiſtants.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro.</note>
               <hi>The eare that heareth you,
bleſſeth you: and the eye that ſeeth you, giues witneſſe to you. The
bleſsing of Her that was ready to periſh, is come vpon you.</hi> Vnder your
ſhadow wee are much refreſhed. The God of bleſsing diſpoſe of your
Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile. <hi>Wee waite for you, as for the raine: and our mouthes are
opened wide, as for the latter raine.</hi> Ita quiſque vt audit, mouetur.</p>
            <p>I need not, neither were it leſſe then boldneſſe and
preſumption in me (Right honourable) to ſuggeſt vnto you, of what weight
and conſequence thoſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires are, which his Maieſty hath been
graciouſly pleaſed to referre to your ioynt conſideration and aduice:
neither need I repeat, how deeply you are all intereſſed<pb facs="tcp:3148:3"/>herein:
you reuerend <hi>Biſhops,</hi> by your ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred profeſsion; you the Noble
<hi>Baronage</hi> of this Realme, by your military honour, alwaies preſt and
ready for the defence of Religion and of this Kingdom, againſt open Inuaders,
or ſecret vnderminers; and you the Repreſentatiue <hi>Body of the
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> in regard of the libertie of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect; but moſt of all,
the free courſe of the Goſpel without impeachment: by whom is not onely
repreſented, but alſo actua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; the deſire and zeale of the body of this
kingdom, being a people true-harted, and feruent toward God in the puritie of
his worſhip; towards our <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> in the ſtedfaſtneſſe of
obedience; and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Lawes,</hi> in wiſhes and hopes that they
ſhall ſtream forth <hi>motu naturali,</hi> in their owne courſe, without
diuerſion or obſtruction.</p>
            <p>But you being at this time imployed about ſo weighty affaires,
how may I, the meaneſt of the <hi>ſonnes of my Mother,</hi> preſume to
interrupt you? Are there not <hi>the Chariots of Iſrael, and the horſemen
of the ſame?</hi> Doe the Lords <hi>battailes</hi> want<pb facs="tcp:3148:4"/>ſupply?
whence ſhould it be expected but from them? But I may ſay, with
<hi>Epicte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus: Your hand euer holdeth an equall ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, and your Sun
ſhineth alike on the poore and rich.</hi> It may be, <hi>one Scout</hi> may
vpon occaſion heare &amp; know what an whole Army hath no preſent notice
of.</p>
            <p>True it is, (and why ſhould I now be aſhamed to manifeſt it
to ſuch an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly?) <hi>An euill and ſcandalous report is gone forth
of mee,</hi> in regard I was the man that was preſent at the Ieſuite
<hi>Drury</hi> his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at the <hi>Black-Fryers.</hi> I was the ſame day
in the fore-noone at the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at <hi>Pauls-Croſſe:</hi> and lighting
vpon ſome Popiſh company at dinner, they were much magnifying the ſaid
<hi>Drury,</hi> who was to preach to them in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone. The ample report
which they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded him, preferring him far beyond any of the Preachers of our
Church, and depreſsing and vilifying the Sermons at
<hi>Pauls-Croſſe,</hi> in regard of him, whetted my deſire to heare his
ſaid Sermon: to which I was conducted by one <hi>Medcalfe</hi> a
<hi>Prieſt.</hi> This being heard of by my Lord<pb facs="tcp:3148:4"/>
               <hi>Arch-biſhop
of Canterbury</hi> his <hi>Grace,</hi> hee ſent for mee within few daies
after; and being before him, found mee inclining to their ſide. I layd open
my ſelfe vnto him and confeſſed I had ſome ſcruples in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.
Wherupon it pleaſed his <hi>Grace</hi> to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford me his holy counſell and
monition: which had that good effect, that albeit my foot was ſtept into the
<hi>Babylonian</hi> pit, yet I often meditated of his Fatherly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions.
Som other ſpeeches I receiued from his Domeſtique Chaplains, D.
<hi>Goad</hi> and D. <hi>Featly:</hi> for which I ſhall be bound euer to pray
for them: their words left <hi>aculeos et ſtimulos; Vade et nè pecca
amplius, &amp;c.</hi> piercing me the more, being recorded in a publicke
narration: which, my check<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſcience did iuſtly take for an
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditement to conuict me, &amp; a Trumpet to reduce me. <hi>Like the
Prodigall, I now returne home with a Peccaui</hi> in my heart, mouth and pen,
to God and our bleſſed Mother the Church of <hi>England:</hi> to both I
ſay, <hi>Pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caui contra coelum et te.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon why I preſumed to preſent theſe lines to your
view, and offer them<pb facs="tcp:3148:5"/>to your hands, ſeemeth to me iuſt,
becauſe ſincere; and excuſable, becauſe in ſome ſort neceſſary,
in that the vaſtneſſe of my fault requireth, foraſmuch as from my
acquaintance on the left ſide, I can expect little leſſe then indignation
and machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations againſt mee by them; whom, partly by my relinquiſhment of
them, but much more by diſcloſing ſome of their proceedings, I am like to
prouoke in a high degree: it behoueth me therefore to chuſe ſuch Refuge, as
may protect mee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their malice. I haue touched (in a manner) nothing
elſe but the behauiour of the Prieſts; whereto, I might haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
ſomewhat of my owne knowledge, concerning the inſinuations &amp;
incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vſed by thoſe of that ſtamp, who profeſſe phyſick:
Who, whatſoeuer they doe vnto the bodies, infuſe into the mindes of many
the Kings Subiects, bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſtempers; whereby thoſe pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents tongues
diſtaſte the wholſome food of our Church, and their hearts are
ſtric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with <hi>antipathy</hi> againſt our preſent State. But theſe
things I thought fitter for<pb facs="tcp:3148:5"/>your Wiſdomes to cure, then for my
weakneſſe to declare; my intent in this Treatiſe, hauing beene to act the
part of vnmasking the vailed fraud of the Ieſuits &amp; Prieſts: wherin if
you ſomtimes diſlike the ſtile, condemn not me for a botcher: for, their
Stories I alter not a ſtitch, but giue you the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lapt vp in their own
clouts.</p>
            <p>If the forme and phraſe I vſe in other places bee
diſtaſtfull, as either too ſharp, or too light and Ironicall for one of
my profeſsion; let my matter bee my Aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, that draweth mee thereunto;
truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that I may be excuſed, if I ſometime light my candle at the
Torch of <hi>Elias,</hi> when he ſindged and ſmoaked out <hi>Baals
Prieſts</hi> from the neſt of the Sanctuary. I ieſt but at their
ieſting, that haue made a ieſt of God, and of his bleſſed Saints in
heauen, by caſting vpon their moſt pure and glorious faces, the cloud, nay,
the dirt and dung of vgly, vnſauory, ridiculous Fables: whereat the ſounder
Chriſtians are ſcandalized, wherewith the weaker are deluded &amp;
captiuated in ſuperſtition, and the very <hi>Iewes &amp; Heathen</hi> are
driuen<pb facs="tcp:3148:6"/>further off from liſtning vnto the true &amp; ſacred
Myſteries of Chriſtian Religion. For ſurely, no ſmall miſchiefe or
danger is it vnto Truth, to haue her precious gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment eeked out with patches
of falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and, vpon pretence of imbelliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to bee dawbed ouer
with the cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-embrodery of cogging Impoſtures.</p>
            <p>In regard of my own particular; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I hope, I ſhall regaine
that good opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which I haue loſt, and no longer bee cenſured by my
friends and others, as at all wauering, inclining and warping to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their
ſide: yet withall, you haue the Character of mine hart, toward the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke
good of our Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. I ſay no more, but God giue you
vnderſtanding in all things. <hi>Ride on with your honours; and, becauſe of
the Word of Truth,</hi> bee courageous and ſtout <hi>Nehemiahs. Such a man as
I, flee? Nehem.</hi> 6.11. The deaw of Gods grace bee vpon you and your
children. And thus, with my vnceſſant prayers for you, I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The moſt humble ſeruant of you all, to bee
commanded in the Lord, IOHN GEE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3148:6"/>
            <head>THE FOOT OVT OF THE SNARE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> reports,<note place="margin">Aug.
<hi>Ciuit. de Dei. l.</hi> 1.</note> that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the <hi>Primitiue
Church,</hi> and in thoſe better times, the Diuell was become both <hi>Leo
apertè ſaeuiens, &amp; Draco occultè inſidians:</hi> by open
and outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous cruelty, hee ſhewed himſelfe <hi>a Lion;</hi> and, by his
ſecret poiſoning of Religion, <hi>a Dragon.</hi> Yet his malicious power
was curbed, and himſelf bound in chains for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeers: ſo that,
notwithſtanding all his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty, Truth, like <hi>a Palme-tree,</hi>
flouriſhed; and Chriſt's Croſſe, like <hi>Aarons Rod,</hi> did
bloſſom, and bring forth much fruit. But now the <hi>old Serpent</hi> is
let looſe, and of late yeers hath acted both the<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3148:7"/>
               <hi>Lion</hi> and the <hi>Dragon</hi> without reſtraint; both by
policy and puiſance, ſtudying to extinguiſh <hi>the light of the
Truth.</hi> Neither haue his attempts been effectleſſe: for, what by
<hi>Magogs ſword</hi> in the Eaſt, and <hi>Gogs</hi> vſurped
<hi>Keyes</hi> in the Weſt, hee hath dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>Truth,</hi> like <hi>a
Doue,</hi> into the holes of the rocks, and baniſhed <hi>Faith</hi> in many
places from among men.</p>
            <p>In Reformed Churches (eſpecially in our Church of
<hi>England</hi>) Gods <hi>Mercy</hi> hath ſupported his <hi>Truth,</hi> euen
amidſt the ſlacknes and careleſnes of the Profeſſors themſelues:
whil'ſt yet ſome, like <hi>Dinah</hi> the daughter of <hi>Iacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 34.2</note> haue loſt their <hi>Virginity,</hi> I mean,
<hi>primam et puram fidem,</hi> their firſt faith, by <hi>going abroad, and
haue returned home im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure.</hi> Some, like <hi>Salomons outlandiſh
women,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 11.4</note> haue brought-in
<hi>outlandiſh Religion.</hi> Many at home, in ſtead of the <hi>voice of
the Faithfull, Come, let vs go vp into the Houſe of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal.
122.1</note> ſay among themſelues, <hi>Let vs go vp to Bethel, and
trangreſſe to Gilgal, and multiply tranſgreſsions.</hi> So that our
Countrey, which ought to bee euen and vniforme, is now made like a piece of
Arras, full of ſtrange formes and colours. But what is the reaſon?
Beſides the drowzineſſe of many <hi>Luke-warm Goſpellers,</hi> there is
a vigilant <hi>Tribe</hi> (I mean, the <hi>Emiſſaries of Rome, and Factors
for the Papacy</hi>),<hi> who are like vnto</hi> Dan, <hi>and are as an Adder
in the path, which bites the horſe, and makes the Rider to fall
backward.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 49</note> They make them, whom they can
get to work vpon by their perſwaſions, to become retrograde, with the 
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3148:7"/>Church of <hi>Epheſus, to leaue their firſt
loue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 2</note> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Apoſtates in matters
of orthodox Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity. Eaſily can they ſteale away <hi>the hearts of
the weaker ſort:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 15.6</note> and ſecretly do
they creep into hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>leading captiue ſimple women loaden with
ſinnes, and led away with diuerſe luſts.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim
3.6</note>
            </p>
            <p>Strange indeed it is to conſider, how That <hi>Wolf-bred</hi>
and Wolf-breeding <hi>Romulus</hi> doth daily ſend-ouer his rauening brood of
<hi>Ieſuites &amp; Prieſts,</hi> to make hauock &amp; ſpoil, &amp; to
conclude a bloudy Cataſtrophe to a direfull Tragedy. <hi>Aſtant &amp;
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, vt</hi> Hannibal <hi>ad portas:</hi> nay, like <hi>Brennus</hi> and
his <hi>Gaules,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. <hi>vid. de</hi> Bren.</note> they
haue not onely ſurprized our Suburbs, but almoſt taken our Capitol.</p>
            <q> 
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Virgil.</note>Galli per dumos aderant,
arcem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tenebant,</l> 
               <l>Defenſi tenebris &amp; dono noct is opacae:</l>
            </q>
            <p>The <hi>Gaules</hi> came ſtealing-in by night through the
Thickets: ſo theſe Bats, in the twi-light of our ſecurity, creep vpon vs,
<hi>defenſi tenebris.</hi> They finde, perhaps, among vs <hi>a ſtill
night</hi> of negligence and drowzineſſe: but they bring-on a greater
night, by the thick cloud and fogge of ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and forgeries;
wherein they enwrap them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and would enſnare vs; who if they ſhould
go on to the height of their hopes, what may wee expect, but <hi>vt notent
&amp; deſignent oculis ad cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem vnumquem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> noſtrum,
&amp;c?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cic. <hi>orat.</hi> 2. <hi>con.</hi>
Catelin.</note> Did they not long ſince, like the <hi>ſonnes of
Belial,</hi> not onely caſt off the yoke of obedience, with a <hi>Nolumus
hunc reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare, Luke</hi> 19.14. but euen clothe themſelues in the robes of
rebellion, with a <hi>Venite &amp; occidamus,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3148:8"/>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 20.14? 
<note place="margin">Gun-powder Treaſon.</note>Witneſſe one
intention of theirs, which muſt neuer be forgotten. And therefore, not
without iuſt cauſe, haue they been of late put in minde of a ſecond
reflecting Tragedy; which met ſo right with them, that well were it, if they
could apply it to themſelues, according to the ſenſe of our Sauiour's
words (which haue been by diuerſe of my friends rung in mine ears, and I
truſt I ſhall ſtill ponder of and remember them), <hi>Vade, &amp;
nè pecca ampliùs, nè deterius contingat tibi: Sinne no
more, lest a worſe thing happen vnto thee.</hi> And ſure, for my owne
particular, I make ſuch application, and will euer conſider, that I had a
faire warning<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ictus Piſcator ſapit.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>to come out from among them; non tam pede, quàm pectore; non tam
gradibus, quàm affectibus;</hi> not ſo much in motion, as in
affection; leauing them to their ſuperſtitious deuotions, and neuer more
partaking with them in any their abominations.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>omne beneficium petit officium:</hi> as in morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
euery benefit is obligatory, and bindes to ſome thankfull duty; ſo more
eſpecially in Diuinity, the wonderfull works of God, extended to all in
general, or to any one man in particular, in regard of ſpeciall protection,
doo binde to a duty of <hi>Thankſgiuing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though I haue long runne vpon the ſcore, and hitherto yeelded to
<hi>Ingratitude,</hi> that crafty <hi>Sinon,</hi> to keep the doore of my lips,
ſo that I haue nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcharged my <hi>conſcience toward God or
man,</hi> yet will I at laſt, with the <hi>alone Lepe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, return to giue</hi> 
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3148:8"/>
               <hi>praiſe.</hi> And ſurely, of thoſe that eſcaped the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
of the <hi>Black-friers</hi> (an Accident for which I haue been much noted, and
often pointed at), none hath greater cauſe to offer <hi>the calues of his
lips,</hi> a gratefull Sacrifice vnto the Almighty, then <hi>my ſelf.</hi>
For, as my <hi>eſcape</hi> was not the eaſieſt; ſo my
<hi>offenſe,</hi> the greateſt: whereof, one mooueth <hi>me</hi> to
<hi>compunction;</hi> the other, to <hi>gratulation.</hi> Being in the midſt
of the Roume that fell, and though that <hi>omnes circumſtantes,</hi> all (in
a maner) that ſtood about me, periſhed in that calamity, and I inuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in
the down-fall, and falling, being couered with the heaps of rubbiſh and dead
carcaſes; yet it pleaſed God to haſten my Eſcape, beyond my owne
expectation and humane vnderſtanding. Surely, when I record this common
down-fall, which wounded others vnto death, and mee but vnto affright, I cannot
but ſtrike my breſt, and look vp into heauen, or rather with the
<hi>Publican,</hi> down to the earth, and ſay, What was there, or is there in
<hi>me,</hi> miſerable man, that the hand of God ſhould ſtrike ſo many
on my right hand and left, and yet ouerpaſſe <hi>me?</hi> Surely I was no
<hi>Lot,</hi> to eſcape out of burning <hi>Sodom;</hi> no <hi>Noah,</hi> to
bee preſerued in a generall Deluge. If the load of ſinne preſſed them
down that fell (alas! farre be it from me to haue vncharitable conceit of their
perſons), that waight ſhould haue ſunk <hi>mee</hi> then deeper than any
of them, not onely to the ground, but vnder ground, to hell it ſelf. But our
good God is Maſter of his owne work, and<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3148:9"/>free Lord of his
owne mercies. Hee beſtoweth them where there can bee no plea of merit. He
ſpared to crop mee in the ſtrength of my yout h, in the midſt of my
wandring vanities, in the act of my bold curioſity. Hee hath prolonged my
daies, that my heart may be inlarged in thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to his glorious
Name; that my feet might bee inlarged, <hi>to walk the way of his
Commandements;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> that my eyes &amp;
vnderſtanding might be opened, to take a full view of humane frauds,
adulterating his truth, and ſo to abhor them. Doth not he that hath plucked
my feet out of the ſnare, and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me from this <hi>ſudden death</hi>
(againſt which our Church hath taught me to pray), deſerue now to be
praiſed, <hi>toto voto, tota vitâ, toto pectore, toto homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne;</hi> in
al my life, with all my ſoule, and with all my ſelfe? Yes ſure, I will
euer take <hi>the Cup of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and call vpon his Name.</hi> I will not
ceaſe <hi>to pay my vowes vnto him,</hi> in deſpight of our ſpirituall
Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie, or any his Aduocates.<note place="margin">I penned and publiſhed
this writing as a monument of my th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fnlneſſe.</note> 
               <hi>It becommeth well the iuſt to bee
thankfull.</hi> For others that eſcaped, I wiſh they would not ſo
preſumptuouſly tempt God, as ſome of them, whom I haue heard re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine,
becauſe they had not a ſhare in this ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And what is the reaſon
forſooth? Becauſe euer ſince that accident befell, at all the places
about the City of <hi>London,</hi> where Prieſts are har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored, which are not
few (there beeing at this preſent, to my knowledge, more then two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of
them, within the City and Suburbes), af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er euery <hi>Maſſe</hi> of theirs, the Prieſt or Clarke 
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3148:9"/>ſtarteth vp preſently vpon the <hi>Benediction,</hi> and
calleth aloud vnto the people, to ſay three <hi>Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſters,</hi> and
three <hi>Aue-maries for the ſoules of thoſe that died at
Black-Friers.</hi> So that they think it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not otherwiſe chuſe, but that
their ſoules muſt be by this time in heauen. And ſure ſo think I, or
elſe they will neuer come thither. For
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>à modo, forthwith,
bleſſed are the dead that dye in the Lord: they reſt from their labors,
&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel.</note> 
               <hi>Bona mors iuſti, propter
requiem; melior, propter nouitatem; optima, propter ſecuritatem,</hi> ſaith
Saint <hi>Bernard.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 103.</note>
Death is to bee deſired, in regard of the reſt, repoſe, and tranquillity,
wherewith it is immediatly accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied: but in the Prieſts erected
Purgatory, <hi>durante commoratione,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suarez <hi>to.</hi>
3. <hi>in</hi> 3. <hi>p. diſp.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> there is nothing but
torture and torment to be expected.</p>
            <p>I cannot, but, by the way, tell you of one that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry narrowly
eſcaped the danger of <hi>Black-Friers,</hi> &amp; accompanied me that night
to my Lodging: his name was <hi>Parker,</hi> one that had beene long a
<hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> and <hi>Factor</hi> for the <hi>Papacie</hi> beyond the
ſeas. Hee told mee by the way, that nothing grieued him more, then that hee
had not beene one of thoſe that dyed by the afore-ſaid miſchance. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at ſhould make him ſo prodigall of
his life, I know not: but ſure, not long after, the Powers diuine cut the
thred of his daies: for, the weeke following, hee beeing the man that muſt
carry the newes ouer the ſeas to <hi>Doway,</hi> and going then to take
Prieſtly Orders there beeing need of a ſupply, F. <hi>Drury,</hi> F.
<hi>Redyate,</hi> and one F. <hi>Moore,</hi> 
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3148:10"/> beeing ſo
vnexpectedly, as they tearme it, <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyred;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The
Prouerb is, Hee that was borne to be drowned, &amp;c.</note> at
<hi>London-bridge,</hi> at his very firſt ſetting for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, M.
<hi>Parker</hi> was drowned, with a kinſwoman of his, bound for
<hi>Briſſels,</hi> there to take on her the habit of a <hi>Nunne.</hi> I
will not comment vpon theſe diſaſters, knowing, that God reſerues to
himſelfe three things; <hi>The reuenge of Iniuries, The glory of deeds, The
Iudgement of ſecrets. Quae Deus occulta eſſe voluit, non ſunt
ſcrutanda: quae autem manifeſta fecit, non ſunt negligenda; ne etenim in
illis illicitè curioſi, et in his damnabiliter inueniamur
ingrati.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Proſp. <hi>de pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>I will iudge of my owne cauſe, and conclude, that the <hi>Mercy
of God was of larger extent to mee, then any other.</hi> None had prouoked him,
or tempted him more: and therefore, where <hi>ſinne abounded, there the mercy
of God hath abounded much more.</hi> He is, <hi>multus ad ignoſcendum,</hi>
according to the Vulgar Latine, and <hi>Becauſe of ſinners, he ſhall be
called merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi> But why ſhould I haue entred into the houſe of
<hi>Rimmon,</hi> or haue partaken with the abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>children of
Ammon?</hi> Why ſhould I, that knew my owne <hi>Fathers Courts,</hi> haue
gone into the houſe of <hi>a ſtranger? Curioſity,</hi> in theſe kindes,
<hi>cannot excuſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caluin. <hi>inſtit.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Bee not deceiued, God will not bee mocked.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb.</note> It is dangerous with <hi>Ecebolius</hi> to bee
troden vnder foot as <hi>vnſauory ſalt.</hi> How great was his glory! how
infinite his beauty <hi>aboue his fellowes,</hi> who could ſay vnto his
<hi>Father; Thoſe that thou gaueſt me, haue I kept, and none of them is
loſt, but the childe of perdition.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 17.12.</note>
               <hi>Holy Father, keepe them in thy name euen them whom thou haſt giuen mee,
that they may be one, as I am!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:3148:10"/>And let mee here admoniſh all ſuch as are
fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile to yeeld vnto <hi>Popiſh perſwaſion,</hi> and are ready to take
vp the old ſaying of the <hi>Chaldees,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mel. can.
in loc. com.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Homo qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ex Iudaeis venit, Sacerdos, neutiquam
decipiet nos:</hi> Such <hi>a Prieſt</hi> will not deceiue vs. Sure, none
ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, though they winde as cloſe as Iuy about a tree, and ſo
inſinuate, as they <hi>ſuck no ſmall aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</hi> They perſwade,
that their houſes are <hi>the houſes of Cloë;</hi> their houſholds,
<hi>the houſholds of One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiphorus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim.
4.19.</note> But truſt you no ſuch vndermining <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites:</hi>
beleeue you not any of thoſe <hi>oyly-mouthed Abſolons,</hi> though they
ſpeake plauſible things, to ſteale away your hearts from <hi>Gods
Truth,</hi> and the Kings <hi>Obedience;</hi> crying as lowd, <hi>The Church of
Rome,</hi> as euer the Iewes did, <hi>Templum Domini, Templum Domini, The
Temple of the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 7.14.</note> Let them not, with
their <hi>golden Calues reared at</hi> Dan <hi>and</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel, <hi>keepe you
from going to ſerue God at Ieruſalem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King.
12.28.</note> Let them not bring you out of loue with your <hi>Dauid,</hi> your
<hi>Gouernour,</hi> and true <hi>Father,</hi> or with our Orthodox &amp;
Reuerend Church of <hi>England,</hi> your <hi>Mother.</hi> Let them not
intrench you with their falſe &amp; lying Fables; the moſt of which you
cannot be ſo abſurd and dull, but to conceiue and confeſſe, that they
are forgeries, and meere fopperies. Weigh but ſome of them in the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of
your vnderſtanding, which in this poore work of mine, out of their moderne
Authors, I haue truly collected, q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oted, &amp; recited; and you will finde, that, according to the old
plain verſe, 
<q> 
                  <l>Qui leuiter credit, deceptus ſaeperecedit.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:3148:11"/>All that they ſtudy, is but Impoſture and
<hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerdemaine.</hi> They will perchance tell you of their ſtrict
<hi>Orders;</hi> that they are <hi>religious men,</hi> of the <hi>ſociety of
Ieſus, Benedictans, Franciſcans, Auguſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, Bernardines, Antonians,
Ioannites, Carthuſians, Praemonſtratentians, Ciſtertians,</hi> and the
like; that they haue diſtinct habits and cuſtomes, differing one from
another; that they profeſſe perpetuall chaſtity, obedience, and wilfull
pouerty, and liue for the moſt part a ſolitary life, and thence called
<hi>Monks.</hi> Oh beleeue them not: they haue <hi>Eſaus hands,</hi> though
<hi>Iacobs voice:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 25.22.</note> notwithſtanding
all their faire pretexts and ſhewes, they are but as <hi>tinkling cymbals,
and greene bay-trees,</hi> whereunto <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> compares the wicked.<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> The <hi>Pope</hi> diſpenſeth with any thing
heere, while they be in our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Their <hi>penury</hi> is turn'd into
plenty: their <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity</hi> becomes charity, for the relieuing
collapſed Ladies wants: their <hi>Friers coat</hi> is a Gold-laced Suit, to
hide their iuggling knauery, and keepe them vnknowne, when they are drunke in
good company; which is not ſeldome with them, as my ſelfe haue ſeene in
ſufficient ouerflowing meaſure, hauing beene their companion <hi>ad
hila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem;</hi> but I proteſt, neuer <hi>ad ebrietatem.</hi> But
thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, a faire outſide at the <hi>Altar</hi> ſhall mend all, to tempt
you to their <hi>Idolatry,</hi> they will ſhew you their <hi>Biſhops</hi>
and <hi>Priests</hi> offering vp the Sacrifice of the <hi>Maſſe,</hi>
attired in holy <hi>Veſtures,</hi> commanded (as they ſay) by a ſacred
<hi>Synod,</hi> which for their perfection are borrowed out of the <hi>Law of
Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:3148:11"/>I am not ſo ſingularly conceited and
fantaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, as to think, that it is not expedient for a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the
Chriſtian Church, by his decent ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit to bee diſtinguiſhed from the
people, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orned with ſome ſacred ſignificant Robe, in the function
and action of preſenting publick pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers vnto God, or executing the ſacred
Myſteries inſtituted by our Sauiour, to indure <hi>ad conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem
mundi.</hi> But to inuent and multiply vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and theatricall habits,
burthenſome in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſuperfluous in ſignification, and
ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in opinion of ſanctity, this may bee the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per dower of
<hi>Mother Rome,</hi> rather then the <hi>beauty of the Kings Daughter, who is
all glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ious within.</hi> What a
Wardrope of habiliments and idle complements, doth the ſuperſtitious
<hi>Maſsing Prieſt</hi> beare about him! the <hi>Amice,</hi> the <hi>long
Albe,</hi> the <hi>Girdle,</hi> the <hi>Stole,</hi> the <hi>Maniple,</hi> the
<hi>Caſtula,</hi> the <hi>Napkin</hi> or <hi>Sudary,</hi> common to inferiour
Prieſts; beſides the <hi>Sandals,</hi> the <hi>purple Coat</hi> with wide
ſleeues, the <hi>Gloues,</hi> the <hi>Ring,</hi> the <hi>Pall</hi> or
<hi>Cope,</hi> the <hi>Crozier Staffe,</hi> a <hi>Chaire</hi> ſtanding neere
the <hi>Altar:</hi> the laſt ſort of which, are more proper to the
<hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</hi> The <hi>Pope</hi> (by the donation of the Emperor
<hi>Constantine</hi> the Great) weareth, in the Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the
<hi>Maſſe,</hi> all the <hi>Robes</hi> vſed by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of
<hi>Rome;</hi> as, the <hi>Scarlet Coat,</hi> the <hi>ſhort purple
Cloake,</hi> the <hi>Scepter,</hi> and the <hi>Triple Diadem,</hi> and wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h theſe hee is arrayed in the
<hi>Veſtry.</hi> Sure I am, that our Sauiour and his Apoſtles, when they
<hi>preached and baptized,</hi> had other kinde of accoutre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:3148:12"/>They boaſt much of their propitiatory
<hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> of the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> which the <hi>Doctors</hi> of
their Church hold fit to bee ſaid in no other Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage then in Latine; yea,
<hi>Rabanus</hi> auerreth,<note place="margin">Raban. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de
cler. inſtit. cap.</hi> 9.</note> that it is no leſſe then
<hi>Sacriledge,</hi> to think of changing it into another <hi>Tongue,</hi>
which the people can vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand. Now their common anſwer for the peoples
not vnderſtanding their publick pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, hath beene, <hi>That the
Prieſt,</hi> who pronounceth them, doth vnderſtand them: but many of their
<hi>Prieſts</hi> cannot themſelues interpret thoſe very prayers which
they powre foorth for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. The <hi>Maſſe-Book,</hi> as it is Latin
to the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> ſo it is <hi>Greek</hi> to the <hi>Prieſt:</hi> and
how <hi>Prayers, vnderſtood</hi> neither by the <hi>one</hi> nor the
<hi>other,</hi> ſhould be other then <hi>a dead Sacrifice,</hi> I cannot
vnderſtand, euen by their owne <hi>Tenents.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1.
<hi>Cor.</hi> 14.16. ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of one, <hi>quiſupplet locum Idiotae,</hi>
ſurely inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that in the Church there ſhould be at leaſt one who
ſhould bee of an higher forme then <hi>Idiota;</hi> but, for ought I
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee, ſome of their Prieſts
muſt bee content in their <hi>Maſſe,</hi> to act two parts in one; both
of the <hi>Guide,</hi> and of the <hi>Idiote.</hi> For I am ſure, ſome of
them whom I haue met withall in this Kingdom, when I haue ſpoken Latine to
them, they haue not beene able to diſtinguiſh whether it were
<hi>Iriſh</hi> or <hi>Welſh.</hi> One of their <hi>wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Doctors</hi> I
will name, called <hi>Courtney,</hi> whom I met withall in
<hi>Lancaſhire:</hi> he was very buſie tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, that <hi>none could be
ſaued without hearing Maſſe;</hi> and that <hi>Chriſt and his
Apoſtles went vp and downe</hi> 
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:3148:12"/>
               <hi>ſaying Maſſe,
in all Villages and Countries.</hi> And I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him, how he prooued that? He
could name no Scripture or Author, but told me, <hi>He had read it in a
Book,</hi> and, perceiuing me ſmile, ſaid, It was in <hi>The Reuelation of
Saint</hi> Iohn. Hearing his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to this, I asked him another
<hi>Queſtion,</hi> which was, What might be meant by the words ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
vſed together in the <hi>Maſſe, Kirie Eleiſon, Chriſte Eleiſon,
Kirie Eleiſon.</hi> He told me, The word <hi>Kirie</hi> ſignified <hi>The
Host; and Eleiſon, Chriſt.</hi> No mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell now, that they maintaine
Ignorance to bee the <hi>Mother of Deuotion,</hi> the old Prouerb beeing
ſtill true, that <hi>They haue golden Chalices,</hi> but <hi>woodden
Prieſts.</hi> Talking another time in London with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Brother <hi>of
his, one Father</hi> Medcalf, who lyes at <hi>a Tobacco-ſhop in
Shoo-lane,</hi> I asked him, why he could not pray without <hi>a Pictures</hi>
He replied, <hi>How can you vnderſtand what manner of man Christ is, but by
ſeeing him? or any Saint, but by their Picture? or how can you pray without a
Picture, but your minde will be carried ſome other way?</hi> Then thought I
vpon that ſentence of <hi>Fulgentius, It a facilè poſsit Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum
comprehendere, quem tota terra nequit apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fulgent.</note> So eaſy was it with him to comprehend Chriſt,
whom the whole world cannot appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend. To goe on with their abſurdities:
<hi>One</hi> F. Leech <hi>a Ieſuite,</hi> who wrote the book called
<hi>Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall Counſailes,</hi> told mee beeing with him in Chriſtmas
laſt, <hi>That if any but heare Maſſe, and after hearing, be ſprinkled
with holy water, and kiſſe the Prieſts garment,</hi> hee could <hi>not
commit</hi> that day any<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3148:13"/> 
               <hi>mortall ſinne, ſi
maximè velit,</hi> though hee would neuer ſo fain. Which indeed,
though very groſſe and abſurd, is no leſſe than ſome of their
Writers auouch.<note place="margin">Barſt <hi>in lib. inſt.</hi> The
Propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, <hi>pag.</hi> 74. <hi>vid.</hi> Fitz-Sim. <hi>in fin. citat. in
diuerſ. loc.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>O how doo they lead along poor ſilly ſoules into the gulf of
deſtruction, by telling them, ſuch and ſuch ſinnes are but <hi>venial;
drunkenneſſe, lying, ſwearing,</hi> and (vpon occaſion)
<hi>forſwearing,</hi> but <hi>venial ſinnes!</hi> whereas no ſins are
leſſer than the point of thoſe thorns that pierced the head of Chriſt:
<hi>pro quibus abluendis, ſanguis Christi ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſus;</hi> for the waſhing
away of which, Chriſt ſhed drops of bloud in the garden, and opened the
ſpouts of bloud on the Croſſe. Our ſinnes, in Scripture, are compared
vnto ſands; which are very ſmall, con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>idering them ſeuerally, and yet the greateſt ſhippe is
ſwallowed vp of them quickly. 
<note place="margin">Lactantius.</note>Euery <hi>ſinne,</hi> in its
owne nature, hath the <hi>ſting of a Viper, and doth wound vs mortally:</hi>
yea, <hi>the leaſt ſin, legally</hi> conſidered, is <hi>damnable;</hi>
though <hi>euangelically, the greateſt of all is</hi> pardonable. 
<note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note>
               <hi>Inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſabilis eſt
omnis peccator, vel reatu originis,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note>And, <hi>Parentes ante-fecerunt
damnatum, quam natum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard.</hi> And ſo I
conclude with <hi>Elias Cretenſis</hi> his words: <hi>Expeccati fumo, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae
ſunt lachrymae.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cretenſ. <hi>in</hi> Naz.
<hi>orat.</hi> 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lying,</hi> in ſome caſes, the Papiſts hold not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to bee no ſinne, but to bee lawfull: and a man may <hi>forſweare</hi>
himſelf before Authority ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, nay, ought to doo ſo, vnder <hi>pain
of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Witnes their Notes<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. in</hi> 23. <hi>c. Act.
Apoſt.</hi>
               </note> vpon the <hi>Rhemiſts Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> 
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:3148:13"/>and diuerſe their Books. According to the Rule of the
<hi>Parthians,</hi> they will keep faith with none, <hi>niſi quantum
expedit,</hi> but as it ſerues their turn. As for <hi>Oaths,</hi> to the
moſt of them, they are no other than <hi>Collars for Munkies;</hi> which,
vpon diſpenſation of Superiours, they ſlip off their necks at their
pleaſure; eſpecially if they be ſuch <hi>State-Papiſts</hi> as haue
been inſpired with Ieſuitical Equiuocations and mentall Euaſions: whom a
<hi>Reuerend Father</hi> of our Church<note place="margin">D. <hi>King,</hi>
Biſhop of <hi>London.</hi>
               </note> doth blazon out by their true Epithets, and
Enſignes of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, ſtiling them
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the falſeſt cozeners of the
world; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with whom no bond of
nature, conſanguinity, allegeance, alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, affiance, wedlock, Oath,
Sacrament, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth good, if they liſt to diſſolue it. <hi>Dij terrae,
ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem terris auertite pestem:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 82.6</note> O yee
<hi>gods</hi> of the earth, purge this Region of the aire, as much as in you
lieth, of theſe peſtilent exhalations. This I the rather obſerue out of
his Writing, becauſe it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to mee, to bee ſpoken not onely
<hi>morally,</hi> at large, vpon generall experience of their dealing, but
alſo (in a ſort) <hi>prophetically,</hi> as by a kinde of
fore-inſtinct;<note place="margin">I meane, the monſtrous Ly tearmed by them,
The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>London</hi> his Legacy.</note> implying, that himſelf,
though not in life, yet in death, ſhould not be free from this their
audacious forgery.</p>
            <p>Let me proceed to a further furuay of their doctrine and religion,
and acquaint you with what I finde true by my owne experience. Sure I am, that
the Papiſts, by diuers their Impoſtures,<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3148:14"/>haue more
diſhonoured Chriſt, than euer he was by any Sect or Profeſſion
whatſoeuer: for, haue not their beſt Doctors, <hi>Bellarmine, Valentia,
Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quez,</hi> with others, been the very Patrons of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Idolatry,
<hi>ſuam perditionem ſentientes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.
<hi>Epiſt.</hi> 48 <hi>ad</hi> Vinc.</note> feeling themſelues to periſh,
and yet would not bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed? <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>Valentia</hi>
maintaining, that <hi>there is a proper worſhip due to Images;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bell. <hi>tract. &amp; cont. de Imag.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Vaſquez,</hi> implying, that the <hi>Diuell,</hi> in ſome caſes,
<hi>may bee adored.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vaſq. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>de
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorat. diſp.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> And howſoeuer, of late yeers,
they will a little refine their doctrine concerning Image<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip, by
Diſtinctions and Metaphyſicall No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, yet the practice of the people
among them (to my knowledge) is no leſſe than <hi>Idolomania;</hi> that
practice, I ſay, not priuate, or forbidden by their Guides, but foſtered,
increaſed, and kindled by thoſe that pretend to be the Fathers and
Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of their ſoules. Reade <hi>Dauies</hi> his Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme,<note place="margin">Dauies <hi>Catec. page</hi> 217.</note> and a Book of theirs,
called, <hi>The Manual of Controuerſies;</hi> and ſee whether they doo not
allow <hi>of falling down to Images, of kiſsing them,</hi> as they doo the
<hi>Pax</hi> in the <hi>Maſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhall I ſay of their much mumbling of
<hi>Maſſes,</hi> and jumbling of <hi>Beads?</hi> If there be twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
Prieſts in a houſe, they muſt all ſay <hi>Maſſe</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Noon,
though there be no body by, though they ſacrifice to the wals. They muſt
haue <hi>beads,</hi> to pray by number, or elſe their prayers want weight.
They are commanded to ſay ſomtimes in one day an hundred and fifty
<hi>Pater-noſters,</hi> as many <hi>Aue-Maries,</hi> forty <hi>Creeds;</hi>
and, if they miſſe<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3148:14"/>but one of the right number, all is
vaine and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectleſſe: nay, the <hi>Confeſſors</hi> hold it to be
<hi>a mortall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inne,</hi> if, among
ſo many Prayers appointed to be ſaid for Penance, one onely be
omitted.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Goddard,</hi> in his Treatiſe of
Confeſſion, page 40.</note>
            </p>
            <p>As concerning their <hi>Proceſsions, Praying to the Dead,
Inuocation of Saints, Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ration of
the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Hoaſt, Adminiſtration of the Sacrament vnder one kinde,
ſprinkling of Holy-water, tinkling of a Bell at the Eleuation, kiſsing the
ground where the Prieſt hath ſtood, worſhipping of Reliques, repeating
the name Ieſus nine times together, with nines vpon nines, often
croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the fore-head and the breſt, their neceſſary wetting of
their fingers in the holy Pot, before they go toward the Altar, their kneeling
down to euery Prieſt they meet, their ambling thrice about a Croſſe,
their Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, Dirges, ſeuerall ſorts of Letanies, in which the Saints
only are inuocated,</hi> and other like traſh, which are the very
<hi>Diana</hi> of the <hi>Romiſh Religion,</hi> what foundation haue they in
holy Scripture? Are they built vpon the Rock Chriſt? No; but vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the
ſands of humane brains; being inuented, and obtruded vpon the people, to
aduance the benefit and honour of their Clergie. So ſaith one of their owne
Writers: <hi>An non audis dicentes grata multitudini, flectentes, fingentes, ac
refingentes religionem ad nutum &amp; c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>piditates Dominorum &amp; coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum; quorum gloriam, niſi ſuam,
pluris faciunt, quam gloriam Dei?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ebber. <hi>in prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. in com. Philip. ſuper Chriſt. ad
Cor.</hi>
               </note> Doo you not heare them, how they ſpeak plauſibly to the
itching eares of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, inflecting, faſhioning and refaſhioning
their religion according to the will and wantonnes of <pb n="18" facs="tcp:3148:15"/>them,
whoſe glory, next vnto their owne, they preferre before the glory of God?</p>
            <p>But ſhall not their owne Diſciples one day
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>peak vnto them, according to that
of Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gustine, Quare nos decepiſtis? Quare tanta mala &amp; falſa
dixiſtis? Et erubeſcunt humanae infirmitati, &amp; non erubeſcunt
inuictiſsimae veritati.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. <hi>ſer.</hi> 22.
<hi>de verb. apoſt.</hi>
               </note> Why did you ſeduce vs? Why did you tell vs
ſo many falſe things; more regarding the weaknes of men, than the
inuincibleneſſe of Truth? Yes ſure: <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt, cùm
dies Iudicij venerit, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyp. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>ep.</hi> 3</note> to your charge, the
loſſe of ſo many ſoules, for which Chriſt gaue his life, will <hi>one
day</hi> bee laid, and a ſtrict account exacted. Many <hi>wauing Babes</hi>
were carried away with the <hi>blaſt of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits,</hi> beaten and broken
againſt the <hi>rock</hi> of errour; many, I ſay, whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi>
tearmeth <hi>Paruulos fluctuantes,</hi> vnconſtant yong-ones; not ſo much
ſwelling with pride, as deceiued and toſſed with the rage of your
Impoſture. But, my beloued <hi>Country-men,</hi> let not fuch <hi>vipers eat
out your hearts:</hi> let not the <hi>ignis fatuus</hi> of their prepoſterous
zeale miſ-lead you: but diſcouer the hypocrites, and ſend them home to
hell, where they were hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. For, they that dare thus dally with God, no
marnell, though they bee bold with your ſoules, conſciences, your children,
and your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and all that belong to you. Many a poore Gentleman, that
cannot rule his wife, I knowe, is faine to weare their mark <hi>in capite;</hi>
and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what they muſt haue <hi>in marſupio,</hi> though the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3148:15"/>lie for it <hi>in carcere.</hi> They muſt bee fed with
the daintieſt cheere, the beſt wine, the beſt beer, the chiefeſt fruits
that can bee got; when oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the poor husband is fain to ſlink away
hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry to his reſt.</p>
            <p>In the end, they proue <hi>Plagiarij,</hi> ſtealing away their
children, and ſending them beyond the ſeas, to their vtter ruine and
ouerthrowe. This is too common a practice. Some friends of mine<note place="margin">One M. <hi>Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> a Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. </note> haue
felt the ſmart thereof. 
<note place="margin">The Prieſts practice with a yong man in
London.</note>I think it will not be amiſſe to inſert, how they dealt
with a yong man heer in <hi>London,</hi> who is <hi>Grand-childe</hi> to the
<hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of York,</hi> about the end of <hi>February</hi> laſt. They
perſwaded him, what a fine life it would bee to liue beyond the ſeas; and
withall told him, that, if hee would go-ouer to one of their Colledges, he
ſhould want no maintenance: and, for that he was not fully grounded in their
religion, he was referred to one to conferre withall. It fortuned, that he came
to that man that muſt indoctrinate him, while I was by. I, ſmelling their
knauery, could not reſt quiet, till I had found out the yong man, and
inquired his buſineſſe with the Prieſts, with whom I had ſeene him
often conuerſant; who preſently tould mee their project, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted
me, that he muſt ſuddenly take his iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: o Saint <hi>Omers.</hi> But,
my ſelf diſcouering vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him diuerſe of their cheats and tricks, and
aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring him, that he ſhould finde the caſe altered, if he went out of
<hi>England;</hi> the young man, being very ingenuous, was deterred, and (I
hope) will<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3148:16"/>haue no more familiarity with them. Some of the
Prieſts Agents dealt in the ſame ſort with a very pretty modeſt Youth,
one <hi>Henry Syluester</hi> (ſonne to the no leſſe worthy than famous
Poet, <hi>Ioſuah Syluester,</hi> the Tranſlator of <hi>Du Bartas</hi>);
who, being a ſcholar at <hi>Suttons Hoſpitall</hi> neere <hi>London,</hi>
was drawn to ſuch places as the Prieſts often frequent, and there had books
beſtowed on him. They inueigled and wrought ſo farre with him, that he
conſented to bee ſent beyond the ſeas. And away they had packed him, but
that their plot was in time diſcouered. Many others haue they of late daies
ſeduced: but, I hope, their Kingdome is now almoſt at an end.</p>
            <p>As for you who haue occaſion to liue neer the wals of theſe
Aduerſaries, and it may bee, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, of neceſſity, muſt
conuerſe and haue ſome commerce with them, take heed you be not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
by them. <hi>Haue no fellowſhip with the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull works of darknes,</hi>
though <hi>with the workers.</hi> Be like vnto the Riuer <hi>Arethuſa,</hi>
which paſſeth through the <hi>Sicilian Sea,</hi> and yet takes no
ſaltnes.<note place="margin">Virg. <hi>eccl. vlt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Liue
blameleſſe in the midſt of a peruerſe and crooked generation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And let me now ſpeak vnto you who are my Brethren of the
Miniſtery, and ſhould (in regard of your office and example) be as Angels
in the Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mament of the Church:
Perceiue you not how hereſie begins to ſpread, as that of <hi>Arrius</hi>
in the daies of <hi>Athanaſius?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Soz.</hi> eccl.
hiſt.</note> 
               <hi>Serpit vt Gangrena,</hi> it creeps as a <hi>Gangrene:</hi>
and yet mourn you not for<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3148:16"/>our <hi>Sion</hi> in her
widow-hood, nor <hi>pray for the peace of Ieruſalem?</hi> Behold you not the
ranke of our hollow-harted Neuteraliſts, who think the time is come, to pull
downe our Culuer-houſe, our little Church? How often haſt thou heard them,
O God (though they whiſpered vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues) ſay of the enemies of our
peace, <hi>Why are the wheeles of his Chariot ſo long a-comming?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iud. 5.28.</note> 
               <hi>Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt diem:</hi> They haue long lookt
for a day. I hope they will but expect, till their very eyes drop out of their
heads. Againe, vnderſtand you not, how laborious and vigilant our
Aduerſaries now are, forbearing no time, ſparing no paines, to captiuate
and deſtroy? Witneſſe the ſwarmes of their bookes, which you may heare
humming vp and downe in euery corner both of City and Countrey. I ſpeak it
with griefe; and in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, <hi>cor meum, tanquam cera
liqueſcens:</hi> my heart is as melting wax. I verily beleeue, they haue
vented more of their pamphlets within this Twelue-month, then they did in forty
yeeres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. They haue <hi>Printing-preſſes</hi> and
<hi>Book-ſellers</hi> almoſt in euery corner. And how doe they by this
meanes put their poore Diſciples vpon the tenters, ſelling that book for
forty or fifty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, which they might affoord for eight or ten; &amp;
that for ten, which they might afford for one? For inſtance, I referre you to
the Cat alogue in the latter end of this book. I ſpeak this by the way, to
diſcouer their extorting policie, who make a Treaſury for themſelues by
theſe means,<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3148:17"/>and raiſe no ſmall ſummes of money. You
are thoſe whom God hath ſet vp as <hi>Lamps</hi> in his Sanctuary, <hi>to
giue light vnto thoſe that ſit in darkneſſe, &amp; in the ſhadow of
death, to guide their feet into the way of Truth:</hi> hide not your glory
<hi>vnder a buſhell;</hi> let not your beauty be eclipſed: but (as the
<hi>Spirit to the Angel of Philadelphia</hi>) <hi>Hold that which you
haue:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>Stand with your loines
girt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.14.</note> 
               <hi>Be ſtrong in the Lord,
and in the power of his might:</hi> and remember, that <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centi dabitur,
To him that ouercommeth, ſhall it be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu.
3.</note> 
               <hi>Nec paranti ad praelium, nec pugnanti ad ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, multo
minùs te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>giuerſanti ad
peccatum, ſed vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centi ad victoriam;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note> Not
to him that prepares to fight, nor to him that reſiſts to bloud, much
leſſe him that ſhewes his back in cowardice, but to him that ouercomes to
conqueſt. And hence Saint <hi>Hieromes</hi> penne, like a Lance, was charged
againſt <hi>Vigilantius</hi> and others.<note place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>eccl.
hist. l.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 22.</note> Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> in his
diſputations, ſpake hot words, coles of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niper, againſt the
<hi>Arians,</hi> the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts,</hi> and the
<hi>Manichees.</hi> Bee you as vigilant and ſeuere: <hi>Res poſtulat,</hi>
the times require it: and therefore beginne to blame the Church <hi>of
Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, for imbracing the doctrine of the Nicolaitans; and the Church of
Smyrna, for imbracing the doctrine of Balaam; and the Church of Thyatyra, for
imbracing the doctrine of Iezabel:</hi> and ſhame not to tell the Lady <hi>of
Rome,</hi> that, notwithſtanding all her pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and complexions vpon her
face, <hi>the cup of fornication is in her hand.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc.
17.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> ſpake as much vnto <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer,
that he was 
<note place="margin">Acts 8.23.</note>
               <hi>in the gall of
bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:3148:17"/>
               <hi>and bond of iniquity; Paul</hi>
vnto <hi>Elymas, O full of miſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iefe, and enemy of all righteouſneſſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 13.10.</note> 
               <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carpus,</hi> to <hi>Marcion,</hi>
calling him <hi>Diaboli primogeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> the diuels firſt-borne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Strabo.</note>
               <hi>Strabo</hi> deſcribeth a
certaine fountaine to be in <hi>Arabia</hi> beyond <hi>Iordan,</hi> which
poyſoneth all Beaſts that drink thereof: for which cauſe it is ordained,
that the <hi>Heardſmen</hi> ſhall make reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for ſuch Beaſts
as periſh by drinking of it; vnleſſe they prooue, by violence they
approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. In like ſort, there is a well <hi>of abomination:</hi> many
<hi>wilde Aſſes</hi> runne thereunto to quench their thirſt: and yet they
that taſte thereof, periſh. The Paſtors of Chriſts flock, who haue
<hi>Peters Paſce</hi> for their charge, if they keepe not their
<hi>Hold,</hi> that is, hould their ſheepe within their fold, their ſoule
ſhall anſwer for the ſame, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it ſhall appeare, they drank the
deadly wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſinne, through their owne wilfulneſſe, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the
others negligence.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Shepheard</hi> cannot ſtep aſide, but the Wolfe is
ready to ſeize vpon his <hi>Flock.</hi> There are many <hi>Wolues;</hi> ſo
termed, not ſo much in regard of the compoſition of their bodies, as the
diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of their mindes; <hi>for they ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll come vnto you inſheepes clothing:
but beleeue them not for inwardly they are rauening.</hi> There are ſubtile
Serpents, that ſtill wait for their booty: <hi>Their poyſon is like the
poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a Serpent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 58.4.</note>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.4. or as the Apoſtle: <hi>Their tongue is full of deadly
poyſon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iames 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>Inficit,
Interficit:</hi> The infection thereof doth not onely beginne of late 
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3148:18"/>to ſpread, but hath left many for dead, that there is
little hope of their reuiuing; <hi>Non aegroti, ſed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functi,</hi> beeing
not diſeaſed, but deceaſed. They are no ſooner <hi>feuerous,</hi> but
their Phyſician holds them to a dyet-drink: they ſhall not haue the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> that would coole them; but <hi>Marah,</hi> the
harſh, bitter, and ill-brewed drink of damnation, to deſtroy them.</p>
            <p>I haue read of one <hi>Exagon,</hi> an <hi>Ambaſſadour to
Rome,</hi> beeing at the <hi>Conſuls</hi> command caſt into a Tunne of
<hi>Snakes,</hi> that they licked him with their tongues, and did him no harme:
But theſe Snakes, though they were ſent vs from <hi>Rome,</hi> bring ſuch
poyſon with them, <hi>non in caudâ, ſed in linguâ,</hi> not in
their taile, but in their tongues, that with their very breath they can infect
and infeſt. How many ſoules haue they ſo killed in our land!</p>
            <q> 
               <l>Aſpidis et morſu laeſum dormire fatentur</l> 
               <l>In mortem, antidotum nec valüiſſe ferunt.</l>
            </q>
            <p>It behooueth vs to bee in our <hi>generation, as wiſe</hi> as
theſe <hi>Serpents,</hi> though <hi>as harmeleſſe as Doues.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10.16.</note> Againſt the incantations of ſuch
<hi>Sirens,</hi> let vs ring the <hi>Muſicall bells of Aaron,</hi> and ſing
the ſweet ſongs of <hi>Sion,</hi> that is, arme our ſelues with the
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of God, treaſured vp in the
Scriptures: ſo ſhall not the <hi>Locuſts of the wilderneſſe,</hi>
with their <hi>Scorpion</hi>-like tayles (who now ſwarme in ſuch
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance) hurt any of our little ones with the deadly ſting of their
contagious error: but, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the ſeale of God in their fore-heads, they 
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3148:18"/>ſhall be able to reſiſt all ſuch as ceaſe not to
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the <hi>Spouſe of Chriſt,</hi> and to make warre with <hi>her
ſeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for the better diſcouery of the impious tricks and deuices
of the Prieſts and Ieſuites, and that all who meet within any of their
moderne bookes (whereof I told you, there is ſuch plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) may hoot at them
for moſt abominable Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtors and lyers. Let mee intreat you to reade a
few of ſuch Tales as I haue culled and collected out of their books lately
ſent ouer, the moſt or all of them according to the fronti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpice printed
at <hi>Doway;</hi> and you would think, any ſolid wit could not be
miſcarried by them, but rather admire the poore ſhifts they are driuen
vnto, for the keeping of their weather-beaten cauſe aflote. So palpably doe
they proceed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the bounds of modeſty and reaſon, <hi>vt nemo eorum
obteſtationibus et iactationibus quicquam credat, nam eos mentiri
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t dupliciter mentiri certiſsimum
eſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Luther.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luth. <hi>defen. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. caen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. Fol.</hi> 381, 382.</note> Let none beleeue their
proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and vaunts: for it is moſt certaine, they lie, and that
lowdly. If they will needs be <hi>Architec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti mendaciorum,</hi> ſtill
hammering vntruths; I would aduiſe them to lay probable foundations, and
chuſe ſuch <hi>Materials</hi> as are more malleable.</p>
            <p>To beginne then with one Tale of theirs, and it is a pretty one,
alleadged by one <hi>Henry Fitz-Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> Ieſuite, in his book called
<hi>The iuſtification and Expoſition of the Sacrifice of the Maſſe,
Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>page</hi> 131.<note place="margin">Fitz-Simons <hi>lib.</hi> 1.
<hi>page</hi> 131.</note>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:3148:19"/>
               <note place="margin">In all the Tales I vſe
their owne words.</note>In <hi>Deepe (ſaith he),</hi> a Towne of
<hi>France,</hi> a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Proteſtant Religion, dandling her infant,
that neuer before could ſpeak; the childe diſtinctly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, To
Maſſe, To Maſſe. The mother, warned ſo admirably, went inſtantly
with the infant in her armes to Church, and found therein a learned man
preaching of Religion. His Sermon beeing ended, ſhee felt her ſelfe ſo
ſufficiently reſolued, that, renouncing her hereſie, ſhee forthwith
became Catholick.</q>
            <p>It pleaſeth God indeed to vſe the <hi>weake</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
to confound the <hi>ſtrong;</hi> to imploy the <hi>child,</hi> to conuert the
<hi>parent;</hi> and to indoctrine the <hi>inno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cent,</hi> to refute the
<hi>inſolent:</hi> but that he ſhould ſhew any ſuch Miracle, for the
iuſtification and ratify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that moſt impious &amp; idolatrous
Sacrifice of the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> is beyond the liſts of reaſon, I may
well ſay, the bounds of <hi>Chriſtian faith,</hi> to beleeue. But for want
of better Argument, you ſhall heare what other Tales haue flowed from the
f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth of their vnderſtanding, to
delude the ignorant, and confirme this ſaid Sacrifice.</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Fitz-Simon <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>part.</hi> 6.
<hi>page.</hi> 402.</note>A Mariner beeing ſuppoſed to bee drowned, a
Biſhop of his Countrey cauſed Maſſe to bee ſaid for him. The Mariner
at that time had beene ſome twenty daies without food, borne vp and downe
vpon the keele of a boat, and then ready for famine to die. In the houre (as
after was knowne) of the oblation for him, a man appeared, and deliuered him a
portion of bread: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3148:19"/>ſuddenly he had full force and
vigour; and ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by a ſhip ſayling by, he was reſcued:
<hi>Fitz-Simon, qui ſupra, Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>part.</hi> 6. <hi>page</hi>
402.</q>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">R.L.P. <hi>in lib. Inſtit.</hi> The moſt
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Sacrifice. Fol. 36.</note>There was a Gentlewoman neere
<hi>Naples,</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> whoſe husband was a Captaine: and ſhee,
ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing tidings that he was ſlaine in a battel, cauſed weekly Maſſes to
be ſaid for him. It fell out, that this Captaine was impriſoned: and after
by good teſtimony it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that at the very ſame time Maſſes were
ſaying for him, his chaines and fetters fell from him, and could not bee
faſtned.</q>
            <p>Let mee help to prompt this Tale-teller, with another of the
ſame Cut. 
<q>A Frier that had more minde to fill his owne purſe, then to
empty Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, did very zealouſly and reſolutely in his Sermon before
his Offering, auouch and warrant his Auditory, that whoſoeuer came vp with
money to the Altar, and would think of any his deareſt friend, whom he
thought to bee a Priſoner in Purgatory, ſhould obtaine this grace by that
indulgence, that at the very inſtant of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys throwne in, and clinking
in the baſon, the ſoule ſhould leap out of Purgatory.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">R L.P. <hi>in lib. praedici. Fol.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The aforeſaid Author
reporteth of another <hi>Priſoner ſuppoſed alſo to bee dead,</hi>
whoſe Brother (beeing an <hi>Abbot</hi>) <hi>ſaying Maſſe for him: his
bands fell alwaies, and could not reſtraine him, whereat his enemies at
length wearied, gaue him liberty to redeeme himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:3148:20"/>
               <hi>Quorſum haec?</hi> Why doe they take
ſuch paines, and imploy their braines vpon theſe Inuentions, namely, to
hook-in the people, and bring greiſt to their <hi>Mill,</hi> that their
<hi>Maſſes</hi> may goe readily away for ready money?</p>
            <p>But theſe former Inventions are but ſlight work, poſted ouer
by ſome Prentice of the coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning trade. Behold heere following a more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
Maſter-piece, wherein a chief Architect, and a more nimble Interpreter of the
Puppets, is brought-in for an Actor.</p>
            <q>A gentle-woman of England, in one of the yeers of <hi>Iubile,</hi>
trauelled to Rome; where beeing arriued, ſhee repaired to Father
<hi>Parſons,</hi> who was her Confeſſor, and he adminiſtring vnto her
the bleſſed Sacrament (which, in the forme of a little Wafer, hee put into
her mouth), obſerued, ſhee was long chewing, and could not ſwallow the
ſame: whereupon he asked her, whether ſhee knew what it was ſhee
receiued? Shee anſwered, Yes, a Wafer. At which anſwer of hers, Father
<hi>Parſons</hi> beeing much offended, he thrust his finger into her mouth,
and thence drew out a piece of red fleſh, which after was nailed vp againſt
a poſt in a Veſpery or priuate Chappell within our Lady-Church: and though
this were done about ſome twenty yeeres ſince or more, yet doth that piece
of fleſh there remaine to bee ſeene, very freſh and red as euer it was.
Witneſſe I. <hi>Markes</hi> Ieſuite, in a book of his written of late,
and intituled, The Examination of the new Religion, <hi>page</hi> 128.</q>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:3148:20"/>Yea, heere is a knocking and long-laſting
lie, worthy to be nailed vpon a poſt or pillory, like the eare of a Rogue or
a railing <hi>Moore.</hi>
               <note place="margin">This <hi>Moore</hi> lately loſt
his eares in <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide,</hi> for ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king againſt the Proteſtant
Religion, &amp;c.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Father <hi>Parſons</hi> was but a ſlender Iuggler, that could
not, without putting his finger into her mouth, ſuborne red for white. I
doubt, that hee that inuented this Tale, had ſometimes beene at the ſhop of
<hi>Cowbuck</hi> the <hi>Smith</hi> (held by ſome to bee the putatiue Father
of <hi>Parſons</hi>), and there had ſeene the bottome hoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of a horſe-foot nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt
the Poſts (which vſe to be the trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Trophies of <hi>Farriers</hi>)
and therfore thought he ſhould meet with ſome that would beleeue, a piece
of raw fleſh could be as ſolid &amp; laſting. But I doe not read, that
this woman was euer poſſeſt with that beliefe, as to adore the
fore-ſaid poſt, with the forged Appendix: and I am glad to finde, euen in
the weaker ſex, more truth, in cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>a Spade, a Spade,</hi> then plain
dealing in her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, that would mock her and others by a trick of
<hi>Leigerdemaine:</hi> and therefore the <hi>Tale-maker</hi> was heere
defectiue. For, to ſhew the acceptation and effect of this Miracle, he
ſhould haue added, that the woman, yea and ſome wiſemen too, adored not
onely the <hi>fleſh,</hi> but euen the <hi>naile</hi> with which it was
crucified or rather <hi>poſtified.</hi> This my new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coyned word fits their
new-found Fable.</p>
            <q>A Letter was ſent vnto Father <hi>Parſons</hi> at Rome,
ſignifying vnto him, that a kinſmans houſe of his heere in England had
beene for the ſpace of forty yeeres<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3148:21"/>together moleſted by
Diuels; but, by one Sacrifice or Maſſe offered by Father
<hi>Parſons,</hi> it was deliuered: and his kinred who liued there, hauing
beene all their life time before zealous Proteſtants, haue all of them
ſince become Catholicks. 
<bibl>Io. Markes, <hi>in lib praedict,</hi> page 130.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>I beleeue, many houſes in England, within theſe forty yeeres,
eſpecially thoſe that pertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the friends and wel-wiſhers of
<hi>Parſons</hi> and his fellowes, haue beene much haunted with ſprites,
not of the kinde of <hi>Fairies,</hi> but of thoſe of whom ingenuous
<hi>Chaucer</hi> ſpeaketh;<note place="margin">Chaucer.</note> that where the
<hi>Limiter Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rciſing
Prieſt</hi> went vp and downe, within his ſtation, there were no diuels nor
Hob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goblins to moleſt, eſpecially the weaker ſex in the night time; the
reaſon he giues is demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, For <hi>See,</hi> 
               <q>There n'is none other <hi>Incubus</hi> but hee.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But this difference I obſerue betweene the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Prieſts of
a courſe thread, and theſe refined Scraphicall Maſters of the
Ieſuiticall Loome: they droue away Spirits only by their preſence: but
theſe can dart out a <hi>Maſſe</hi> from ouer Sea, ſome thouſand
miles off, and with it blow away all the diuels that dance in ſuch or ſuch
an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted Caſtle in <hi>England;</hi> whereupon, all the Proteſtants
that dwell within kenning, muſt needs turne <hi>Romaniſts: Teste me
ipſo,</hi> quoth the Diuell.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:3148:21"/>There was a man in <hi>Corduba,</hi> within
the con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ines of <hi>Spain,</hi>
aged foureſcore yeers and odde; who for the ſpace of thirty yeers, had been
in a dead palſie, and bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and then had a burning deſire to heare
Maſſe and to haue the Biſhops bleſsing; and ſo cauſed himſelf, by
his ſeruants to be tranſported to S. <hi>Stephens</hi> Church. The
Maſſe heard, and he born back to his houſe, within few daies he (to all
mens admiration) became whole and ſound, and was as luſty as a man but of
twenty yeeres. He liued eighteen yeers after: during which ſpace, hee came
euery day thankfully to the ſaid Church, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the miracle. 
<bibl>
                  <hi>Kelli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
in a Treatiſe of his, called, Gods bleſsing, page 71.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>At <hi>Corduba</hi> in <hi>Spain?</hi> A Palſie, and yet
foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and eighteen yeers? I am glad it is ſo farre off: I hope they
will haue mee excuſed, for tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelling ſo farre to enquire the truth. And
yet, in another reſpect, I ſhould wiſh to liue in that aire, where
Maſſes grow ſo medicinall, that they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long a mans life, till hee and
all his friends bee weary of him: like the Iles of <hi>Arren</hi> in
<hi>Ireland,</hi> which will not let the candle of our life bee blowne out,
though it be in the ſnuffe: whereof a blundering Frier wrote, <hi>Vbi tam diu
viuunt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines, ita quod habeant taed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um de ſuo viuere.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Leo Tuſcus,</hi> a Confeſſor, Martyr, and Pope, vpon a
certain time was tempted by a woman, who would needs kiſſe him; but the
holy man by no means conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3148:22"/>to ſuch immodesty: yet,
with much ſtruggling, ſhee kiſſed his hand, whether he would or no.
Whereupon, he commanded it to bee cut off, becauſe no corrupt fleſh
ſhould remain about him. Which when the people per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, they earneſtly
interceſſed our Lady for him; and ſhe moſt mercifully reſtored it
again: and then hee ſaid Maſſe as before, and acknowledged our Lady his
Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In lib. in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it.</hi> The liues of the Martyrs,
<hi>tranſl.</hi>
               </note>
            </q>
            <p>If our <hi>ſacrificing Priests</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſuites</hi> ſhould exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute ſo
ſeuere a Law vpon themſelues, the King would haue in this City many
Subiects not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>inwardly</hi> lame in their <hi>obedience,</hi> but
alſo <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly</hi> lame in their <hi>lims.</hi> I knowe two
<hi>Prieſts</hi> in <hi>London,</hi>
               <note place="margin">F.H. F.M.</note> who
are very vnable at this time to doo the King any ſeruice in the warres; for
which, they haue a <hi>neceſſary</hi> excuſe, though not <hi>legall,</hi>
ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing imployed themſelues in other <hi>hot warres</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: ſo that
now they are fitter for an <hi>Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall,</hi> than the <hi>Camp.</hi> And
yet when the time of their <hi>Lying-in</hi> is expired, they will creep out of
the ſhell again, and look as bold as their brethren, laying it on with
<hi>Maſſes,</hi> in ſtead of <hi>muskets.</hi> Yet (mee thinks) they
ſhould vſe very fauourably their judical power in <hi>Confeſsion,</hi>
who themſelues haue had ſo much need of <hi>Indulgence.</hi> To ſay
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of <hi>a Catholique Maid,</hi> ſuppoſed to haue been, with others,
oppreſſed in the ruine at the <hi>Black-Friers;</hi> whoſe office hath
been to carry bands and ſhirts vnto the <hi>Prieſts</hi> chambers: but,
whatſoeuer her ill luck hath been, ſhe hath met with ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious 
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3148:22"/>blaſting vapours, which now ſequeſter her from all
company; being poſted off, by her <hi>Ghoſtly Fathers,</hi> vnto the
Phyſicians.</p>
            <p>But to leaue theſe noiſome corners, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the more
pleaſing path of our old won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-working Tales: He had need be a good
Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion, who could cement a broken piece, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially <hi>a hand</hi>
ſo long <hi>cut off.</hi> But this is like vnto the Tale of Saint
<hi>Dominick; whoſe legs cut off at the knees,</hi> by <hi>praying</hi> vnto
our Lady, they were, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of any Artiſt, graffed on again;<note place="margin">Read, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning S. <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick,</hi> a Book written by a
<hi>I. Heigham,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit. The life of S. <hi>Katharine</hi> of
<hi>Siena.</hi>
               </note> or like that of Saint <hi>Denis,</hi> who, for a mile or
two, carried his head in his hand; or not vnlike the Story of Saint
<hi>Winifred:</hi> of whom they report, <hi>Her head, once cut off, ſprung
and grew on again;</hi> but lopt off a ſecond time, where it fell, there
aroſe a fine ſiluer ſtream, or a pleaſant Fountain of run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning water,
which at this day (as they vaunt) cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Diſeaſed: and the drops of
bloud which Saint <hi>Winifred</hi> there loſt, are yet to be ſeen. The
place of this <hi>beheading,</hi> and where the <hi>miracle</hi> is more
extant, is at <hi>Holiwell</hi> in <hi>Wales,</hi> not many miles off the City
of <hi>Cheſter:</hi> whither once euery yeer, about <hi>Mid-ſummer,</hi>
many ſuperſtitious <hi>Papists</hi> of <hi>Lancaſhire,
Staffordſhire,</hi> and other more remote Countries, go <hi>in
pilgrimage,</hi> eſpecially thoſe of the feminine and ſofter ſex, who
keep there their <hi>Rendeuouz,</hi> meeting with diuerſe Prieſts their
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance; who make it their chief Synod or Conuention for Conſultation,
and <hi>promoting the Catholique Cauſe,</hi> as they call it; yea, and
account<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3148:23"/>it their chiefeſt <hi>harueſt</hi> for commodity
and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, in regard of the crop they then reap by <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions</hi>
and <hi>Indulgences.</hi> Let me adde, that they were ſo bold, about
<hi>Mid-ſummer</hi> the laſt yeere, 1623. that they intruded themſelues
diuers times into the Church or publick <hi>Chappell</hi> of <hi>Holiwell,</hi>
and there ſaid <hi>Maſſe</hi> without contradiction. It is not vnlike,
they will eaſily preſume to the ſame liberty heer in <hi>England,</hi>
which they haue vſed of late in <hi>Ireland;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The bold at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of the Papiſts in
<hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note>where <hi>they diſturbed the Miniſter at a
Funerall, erected one or two Frieries,</hi> with open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, in their
Monaſticall habits, and haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded <hi>titular Biſhops,</hi> to
ſupplant the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gouernment there in force: as we ſee in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<hi>old M. Biſhop,</hi> ſometimes Priſoner in the <hi>Gate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe,</hi>
now perking vp and flanting with the vain, aeriall, fantaſtick bubble of an
<hi>Epiſcopall Title,</hi> far fetcht, and yet lightly giuen, hath rambled vp
and down <hi>Staffordſhire, Buckinghamſhire,</hi> and other places, 
<note place="margin">The Biſhop of <hi>Chalcedon.</hi>
               </note>vnder
the name of the <hi>Biſhop of Chalcedon;</hi> catching the ignorant, vulgar,
and deuoted <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts</hi> with the pomp of his Pontificall Attire, and
that empty name of a <hi>Biſhoprick:</hi> whereunto he hath as much right, as
he hath Lands there.</p>
            <p>I commend the thriftineſſe of the <hi>Popes
Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> in erecting <hi>Biſhopricks</hi> with ſuch ſmall
coſt. The <hi>Title</hi> ſtands him in nothing but a piece of parchment,
with a Boſſe of <hi>Lead,</hi> ſigned <hi>ſub an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulo
Piſcatoris.</hi> As for <hi>iuriſdiction</hi> and <hi>reuenues,</hi> there
needs nothing, but to ſend into <hi>England</hi> this new <hi>Puppet</hi> of
his owne making. The <hi>honeſt, libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:3148:23"/>
               <hi>Pope-holy, Lay-Catholiques</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> many of them,
eſpecially the more ignorant, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dotingly deuout, are ſo mad of
theſe trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries, and ſo ſick of their money, that his
<hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, Beads, Rings, Reliques, Agnus Dei,</hi> and the like, will
be good Merchandize, better (perhaps) than <hi>Virginian Tobacco,</hi> and
feeding as much as that fume. <hi>Phyſicians</hi> ſay, and experience
ſhews, that, for a <hi>Conſumption, Aſſes milk is not the worst
Cure:</hi> and ſure, to feed a-freſh the declining and ſtaruing fopperies
of Popery in this Land, what better nouriſhment, than thoſe no ſmall
ſummes which are daily ſqueezed from many ſimple burden-bearing
<hi>Animals,</hi> whoſe radicall moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of their purſes is daily
exhauſted by the <hi>Horſe-leeches</hi> of <hi>Rome?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The name of <hi>Rome</hi> is able to theſe weak and bleared eyes
to imbeliſh any thing, to gild-ouer and make acceptable any Pils, though
being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but ſheeps trittles. A bundle of <hi>Beads</hi> worth
three pence, if ſanctified from <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhall ſtrain out of
Catholick purſes ſo many pounds. The <hi>Preaching,</hi> the <hi>Liturgie
of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> is but dry meat, and hath no poiſon in it,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not baſted by the cookery of the <hi>Popes Court.</hi> The
<hi>catechizing of children</hi> heer is vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, becauſe not performed
by the ſublimated, pedanticall Inſtructers, the <hi>Ieſuites;</hi> ſuch
reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Fathers as <hi>Ledeſme, Vauſe, Dauies, Cox, Cortin.</hi> The
<hi>confirmation</hi> of our <hi>children</hi> by our <hi>Engliſh
Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> though done in decent form, and with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient 
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3148:24"/>praier, yet (forſooth) hath no ſacred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence,
becauſe our <hi>Biſhops</hi> haue <hi>no Crozier ſtaffe, no Holy water,
no Vnctions, no Chriſme, no binding of foreheads for ſeuen daies, no
deligate Authoritie</hi> à DOMINO DEO NOSTRO PAPA. But, if an
<hi>Eutopian, Chalcedonian, New-nothing, Puffe-paste Titulaedo</hi> come with
faculties in his budget from <hi>Rome,</hi> where he was miraculouſly
<hi>created ex nihilo,</hi> then what gadding, what gazing, what proſtration,
to receiue but one drop of that ſacred deaw! The leaſt flaſh of light
from the ſnuffe of <hi>a Roman Lamp,</hi> out-ſhines and eclipſeth all
the twinkling petty ſparks of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Strange it is,
that any of our Nation ſhould ſo baſely degenerate, as to captiuate their
wits, wils and ſpirits, to ſuch a foraine <hi>Idoll Gull;</hi> compoſed
of palpable fiction and diabolicall faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cination; whoſe enchanted Chalice
of heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Drugges and <hi>Lamian</hi> ſuperſtition hath the power of
<hi>Circes &amp; Medaeas</hi> cup, to metamorphize men into Bayards and
Aſſes. The ſilly, doting <hi>Indian Nation</hi> fall down and perform
diuine ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to <hi>a rag of red cloth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Damianus
à Goes, <hi>de mor. Gent. l.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The fond and braine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick Papiſts of our
Nation doo little leſſe, when they adore the very <hi>Cope</hi> and
<hi>Vestments</hi> (belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to Biſhops and inferior Prieſts) where they
lie alone, falling down to them, and <hi>kiſsing them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to view their new-intruding <hi>Hierarchy</hi> a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
neerer: Me thinks, the <hi>Ministers of the Prouince of Canterbury,</hi> now
meeting in <hi>Conuocation,</hi> are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry forgetfull, in ſuffering
themſelues to be deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3148:24"/>
               <note place="margin">The new
<hi>Arch-deacons</hi> of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Lancaſhire.</hi>
               </note> of a
worthy member, the new-ſtampt <hi>Arch-deacon of London, M. Collington;</hi>
who, by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience he hath had in <hi>exerciſing Iuriſdiction</hi>
ouer his <hi>fellow-Prieſts,</hi> as alſo in <hi>conuenting</hi> the
<hi>Laicks,</hi> is able, if hee were called by authority to the
<hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod,</hi> to giue very good aduice for <hi>reformation,</hi> or
<hi>deformation of the Church of England,</hi> and laying it vnder the
<hi>Popes ſacred foot.</hi> The like defect alſo is in the <hi>Prouince of
York,</hi> by the abſence of the <hi>Arch-deacon of Lancaſter, M. Cli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ton.</hi> No doubt, theſe two new
Chips, clouen out of the old Block of <hi>Rome,</hi> are the onely ſound
Timber to build vp our Church, or rather to make <hi>worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woodden Images,</hi>
for beſotted <hi>Laicks to adore.</hi> I now haſten to acquaint you with
another of their tales, and it is a crafty one.</p>
            <q>A poore old man in <hi>Rome,</hi> loſt his vpper gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and
beeing vnable to buy another, he came to the ſhrine of the twenty Martyrs,
and prayed alowd vnto them to help him to rayments. At his departure, he met
with one at the very Church dore a Prieſt, who deliuered vnto him from the
Pope a Purſe, that had in it to the value of ſome twenty pound in ſiluer.
The poore man amazed, and not knowing what he meant hauing neuer before in all
his life-time had the carriage of ſo much money; the Prieſt told him, Our
holy Father the Pope commanded me to deliuer it vnto the next man I met going
into the Church-dore, who ſhall haue need of it, and bid him ſtill pray to
the Martyrs. The poore man returnedioyfully to his home, and euer after
viſited the place once a day. <pb n="38" facs="tcp:3148:25"/>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Thomas Lee,</hi>
in Tract. de Inuocat. et Adorat. San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor. <hi>Cap.</hi> 14. <hi>page</hi>
212.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>I ſee no reaſon why this ſhould come into the Legend of
ſtrange Narrations, for that the Popes eares might eaſily bee ſo long, by
the Prieſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, without any inſpiration from heauen, as to take
notice of the poore mans deſire, who (belike) was not ſo cold for want of
his coat, as hee was warme with zeale, to cry alowd for a new. But this by the
way. I learne the Popes price of Martyrs, namely, that they are worth pounds
apiece. Well might the Pope haue rated them at a higher value, whenas he
yeerely, nay, daily getteth farre more in their names, by bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering their
pretended Supererogations of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs and Saints.</p>
            <q> In the yeere of our Lord 1612. one <hi>Lucia,</hi> an Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian
Virgin, came to a Towne called <hi>Multauia,</hi> in <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> where
is taught the Waldenſian doctrine, firſt preached to them by one <hi>Iohn
Hus,</hi> and by him general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiued; wherby the traditions of the Romane
Church are at this day there vtterly neglected. This Virgin vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of
diuers their ſtrange opinions, that they denied Purgatory, Prayer for the
dead, Benedictions, and hallowings of Water, the obſeruing of Faſting
daies, and the like; ſhee ſpake ſomewhat diſgracefully of their
Religion: whereupon, ſhee was adiudged and appointed by the Magiſtrate, to
bee burned in a field neere vnto the Towne where ſhee then remained. But the
maid not<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3148:25"/>willing to bee led by them vnto the place of
Execution, they began to tie ropes about her, and ſo to force her along: but
ſhee often croſsing herſelfe, and inuocating the bleſſed Virgin,
Mother of God, could not bee remooued by the ſtrength of ropes, or Oxen, or
any power they vſed. At length ſhee vaniſhed from them, and by a Miracle
was brought vnto a Nunnery, about an hundred miles off that place; where, to
this day ſhe liueth, to praiſe God for her deliuerance. 
<bibl>
                  <hi>Richard Stannihurſt,</hi> in the Preface of his Book,
intituled, The Principles of Catholique Religion.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Hee that made this tale, had a <hi>Chimaera</hi> in his
braine.</p>
            <q> 
               <l>Deſinet in piſcem mulier formoſa ſuperne.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Hee had heard of an old Fable of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> of the
Image of <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Liuium <hi>de
Veſt. virgine.</hi>
               </note> that was to bee brought into the City of
<hi>Rome,</hi> but by no means would it ſtirre, though drawne with ropes,
till there came a <hi>Veſtall Virgin,</hi> that with her girdle drew it after
her. This botcher patcheth ſuch a one together, and fittens; that, in ſtead
of an immoueable Image drawne by a <hi>Virgin,</hi> heere is a <hi>Virgin</hi>
that could not bee drawne like the Image. <hi>And ſo he got a piece of bread
and cheeſe, and came away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A tale to ſome ſuch purpoſe, is repeated of one
<hi>Clarence</hi> a ſacred <hi>Virgin,</hi> by the ſaid Author;<note place="margin">Stannihurſt. <hi>vt ſup.</hi>
               </note> the one as well to bee
beleeued, as the other: yet of both I ſay to the Relator, <pb n="40" facs="tcp:3148:26"/> 
               <q> 
                  <l>Cui tua non odium, velcui portenta cachinnum</l> 
                  <l>Non moueant poſthac, is mihi prodigium eſt.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <q> One <hi>George Sephocard,</hi> a Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>iſh Proteſtant happened to trauaile into
<hi>France,</hi> with a Brother of his: where ſeeing them one day goe in
Proceſsion, this <hi>George</hi> ſcoffed at them, but accordingly he was
rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: for preſently he fell to a pitifull ſcreeching, and ſo died.
The night after his death, <hi>Iohn Sephocard</hi> his brother, and companion
into that Countrey, had a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Viſion. He thought hee ſaw a thouſand
Diuels in hideous and vgly ſhapes tormenting his dead Brother. But he, hauing
had a faire warning thereby, changed his former Religion and courſe of life,
and became Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick. 
<bibl>
                  <hi>F. Baker</hi> in his Watch-word, <hi>page</hi>
20.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Heere is a Proceſſion of lies, one after an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, <hi>ordine
longo.</hi> But yet, that a man ſhould ſmile at their
<hi>Proceſsion,</hi> is not ſtrange; nor that hee ſhould <hi>die,</hi> no
maruell; nor that another ſhould <hi>dreame,</hi> no great wonder: but they
had beſt take heede, how they apply theſe narrations of vnexpected deaths,
leſt the <hi>Story of Black-Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> be aſwell inuerted vpon them.</p>
            <q> 
               <hi>Oſwald Mulſer,</hi> in the County of <hi>Tiroll,</hi>
neere <hi>Oënipont,</hi> would not be contented but with a Prieſtly
Host: hee receiued it no ſooner into his mouth, but hee beganne to ſink
into the ground, which ſwallowed him aliue. <pb n="51" facs="tcp:3148:26"/>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Fitz-Simon</hi> in his Iuſtification and Expoſition of
the Sacrifice to the Maſſe, <hi>page</hi> 100.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>This is a meere fiction, intended for the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying of the
<hi>Priest-hood:</hi> it is the ſteame of their impious policy,
<hi>adterrorem incutiendum, et fucum faciendum populo;</hi> to gull, terrifie,
and amaze the ſimple, ignorant people, and by bringing them into admiration
of their Prieſt-hood, the ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of their attire, and the diuine
potencie of their Sacrifice; by this meanes to inchaunt and bewitch their
innocent ſimple ſoules, and ſo to offer them vp for a prey to their great
Idol at <hi>Rome.</hi> Surely our Sauiour Chriſt ate of the ſame hee gaue
to his Diſciples: but our ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated Prieſts will haue finer bread then
is made of wheat. I maruell, none of our people in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſink
into the ground, for daring to eate of the ſame bread with the
Miniſter.</p>
            <q> 
               <hi>Francis Zauier,</hi> Apoſtle of the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi>
and Ieſuite, as often as hee extraordinarily trauelled in the
<hi>Indies,</hi> ſo often did a Crucifixe in <hi>Spaine,</hi> in his parents
houſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſweat. At length, when the <hi>B. Bauiere</hi> dyed, the
afore-ſaid Crucifixe, during a yeere after, did euery Friday ſweat bloud. 
<bibl>
                  <hi>Hen. Fitz-Simon</hi> in Lib. praedict <hi>page</hi>
123.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Hee had read, be like, the verſe of the <hi>Poet:</hi> 
               <q> 
                  <l>In templis ſudauit ebur pecudeſque loquuti</l> 
                  <l>Infandum.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <q> 
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:3148:27"/>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 36. of <hi>Henry</hi> the
Eightth, a Priest did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce at <hi>Pauls Croſſe,</hi> and there
confeſſed in publick, that he himſelfe ſaying Maſſe, pricked his
finger, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bloudied the Corporas with the Altar-clothes, purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to
make the people beleeue, that the Hoſt had bloud miraculouſly.</q>
            <q> One <hi>Epachius</hi> a Prieſt, on Chriſtmas Eeue, being at
<hi>Martens,</hi> reſorted often to his owne houſe to drink, euen after
midnight: whereby hee was made incapable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the bleſſed Sacrament
on Chriſtmas day, as hauing in the beginning thereof, at midnight, broken the
Faſt. The chiefe of the Towne beeing allied vnto him, not knowing of ſuch
his intemperance, deſired him to ſing Maſſe. Hee, as hee was
preſumptuous, vndertook to celebrate. But as hee receiued the heauenly
Hoſt, ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly hee began to ney like a horſe, to tumble and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low on
the ground, to fome at the mouth, and to deliuer vp the bleſſed Sacrament,
which hee was not able to ſwallow: vpon the diſgorging of which, it was
ſeene to bee carried away viſibly in the aire. The Prieſt beeing in this
plight, hee was by his kinred borne out of the Church, remaining ſubiect to
the falling-ſickneſſe all his life. 
<bibl>
                  <hi>Surius</hi> in vita S. <hi>Godefridi.</hi> l. 3. c.
12.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>It ſeemes to me no more ſtrange now to heare of a drunken
Prieſt, of the Ieſuiticall <hi>fraternity,</hi> then when I read <hi>Petrus
Cluniacenſis Abbas</hi> his book: in which hee reports,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> of ſome forty and odde
<hi>Benedictan Monks,</hi> and <hi>Dominican Friers,</hi> 
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:3148:27"/>that were moſt famous and notorious <hi>Letchers</hi> and
<hi>Bredenbachius</hi> hath a Catalogue of others, who were
<hi>Coniurers;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>collat. ſacr.
c.</hi> 13. <hi>et</hi> 45.</note> 
               <hi>Thomas à Cantiprato,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Th. à Cantip. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>de proprutat. Apum
part.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 40.</note> of diuers others, who were very wicked
and carnall, one of which had his mouth and noſe putrified, that none could
tolerate to look on him: another of which, a fire from heauen conſumed the
hands and armes to his cubits, during his beeing at the Altar. <hi>Petrus
Damianus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pet. Dam <hi>ſpec. exempt.</hi> D. 1.
<hi>F.</hi> 77.</note> and <hi>Palladius</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pallad. <hi>in
hiſt. Lauſiaca, ſect.</hi> 17.</note> report of ſix other Prieſts
that were <hi>Sodomites;</hi> one of which was hideouſly deformed with a
canker, another deuoured of a wilde beaſt, and the reſt miſerably ended
their daies. All this is ſtoried by their owne Writers.</p>
            <p>Seuerall Miracles haue beene done in <hi>England</hi> and
elſe-where, ſaith F. <hi>Richard Conway</hi> the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite, by <hi>the
honouring of Saints Reliques;</hi> which Proteſtants (ſaith he) will not
heed.</p>
            <q>One M. <hi>Anderton,</hi> a Lancaſhire Gentleman, was cured of
the Stone, by the Reliques he had of F. <hi>Campi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> the bleſſed
Saint: &amp; being afterwards of another diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, laid out ſo for dead
<hi>(vt ei iam pollices ligaren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur)</hi> that his thumbes were bound; by the
help of the ſaid Martyr, his fleſh beeing laid vpon his body, he was
raiſed to life. 
<bibl>Rich. Conway <hi>in Apol</hi> pag. 281.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">This is like vnto diuers the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
Fables, which you ſhal finde in the Reuelations of Saint <hi>Bridget,
lib.</hi> 4. or like that of <hi>Vegas</hi> the Frier, in comment. <hi>in
cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Apoc.</hi> Aug. <hi>de vera relig.</hi> Gregor. <hi>hom.</hi>
29. <hi>in Euang.</hi> Paul. Bombin. <hi>in vit. Mart.</hi> Campian.</note>What
prodigies are theſe? What horrible imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s? Are they not
<hi>Anti-chriſti &amp; Pſeudo-chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti,</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:3148:28"/>that
breathe out theſe damnable forgeries? that ſhame not to affirme, that the
bones of a <hi>Traytor</hi> can <hi>raiſe a dead man,</hi> as did
<hi>Elias</hi> his bones? or that the <hi>fleſh of Campian,</hi> could
performe that which was ſo much admired in our Sauiour himſelfe, when hee
was amongſt <hi>vs in the fleſh?</hi> How can they but bluſh at theſe
things? When Father <hi>Campian</hi> came an <hi>Apoſtle into England,</hi>
there was an <hi>Earth-quake</hi> (ſay they) and ſo there might well bee.
Nay the <hi>great bell of Weſtminſter tould of it ſelfe. But that I think
is a lye.</hi> When Father <hi>Campian</hi> was arraigned, Iudge <hi>Seth his
finger burſt out a-bleeding through his gloue, Thames ouerflowed,</hi> and
diuers other obſeruations haue our impoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing Renagadoes. But thoſe
ſaltleſſe gulleries are no whit anſwerable to this their villainous and
prophane fiction. If M. <hi>Anderton</hi> were thus ſtrangely raiſed, it is
maruell his friends in <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> ſpeake not of it, with many of
whom I conuerſed, &amp; am ſure (had it bin true) would haue recited this
tale in their diſcourſe. Againe, if <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques</hi> bee thus powerfull,
I wonder they had not tryed, &amp; brought ſome of them for the reuiuing of
their <hi>Prieſts,</hi> or any other of them that were killed at the
<hi>Black-Friers:</hi> or why made they not vſe of ſome of them, for the
curing of <hi>Lady Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones,</hi> and ſuch as were, by the miſchance
at the <hi>Black-Friers,</hi> ſore wounded?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Campians Saint-ſhip</hi> ſure came but from
<hi>Tiburn.</hi> And yet what admirable vertue doe our Papiſts conceiue to
bee in the poore Reliques of <hi>Story,</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:3148:28"/>
               <hi>Felton,
Sommeruile, Ard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, Parry, Lopez,
Garnet, Campian,</hi> and the reſt of that <hi>Saint-traitorly</hi> Cru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? The very paring of their nailes doth
help <hi>to doo miracles.</hi> Their pictures are ſo ſanctified, that they
are hung ouer the Altars. And I much maruell, there were neuer ſtrange
wonders performed by the <hi>wood of the Tree</hi> at <hi>Tiburn;</hi>
conſidering, it hath been bleſſed by ſome of their ſacred bodies, and
bedewed with their laſt ſpritefull breath. 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Campians</hi> gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle.</note>But did you
neuer heare of <hi>Campians girdle that hee wore?</hi> Then reade one
<hi>Edmunds</hi> his book of <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles,</hi> and that will tell you
ſtrange newes: <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſolyma (inquit) bene nouit ad quem pertinuit:
Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnus non ignorat, qui locus erat vbi Pater ipſe</hi> Campianus
<hi>martyrio coronatus erat:</hi> Ieruſalem (quoth hee) knowes this girdle:
for, it girded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about the Sepulchre of our Sauiour. Tiburne knowes it, the place
where <hi>Father Campian</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his crown of martyrdome: yea, ſaith
he fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the <hi>Diuels</hi> knowe it, who deteſt all ſuch manner
of geere, and whom it hath vexed ſo ſore, that it hath put them to extreme
torments. This Girdle cured <hi>Lepers, the blinde, the dumb,</hi> all manner
of diſeaſes. If the Girdle that imbraced onely his bare apparell, could doo
ſuch miracles, what then ſhould I think of the Rope that imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<hi>Father Campian</hi>'s holy neck? yet I heare of no wonders done by that.
The beſotted <hi>Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> that kiſſed, with earneſt deuotion,
the <hi>Aſſe</hi> vpon which the <hi>Idoll Iſis</hi> ſate; and the
lymphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <hi>Priests</hi> of <hi>Baal,</hi> that lanced their owne fleſh
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3148:29"/>before an Idoll of wood, had as much religion, and I think
more wit than our moderne <hi>Relique<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauers</hi> haue. God hath giuen them
ouer <hi>to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of illuſion,</hi> to beleeue vnſauory lies.
<hi>He that ſits in the heauens, laughs them to ſcorn.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal.</note> Almighty God, with his <hi>Angels</hi> and
<hi>Saints,</hi> will haue them (theſe miſ-ſhapen monſters) in
deriſion.</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Conway <hi>in apol. pag.</hi> 290.</note>A
Virgin, a kinſwoman of mine, <hi>ſaith</hi> Conway <hi>an</hi> Engliſh
Prieſt, was freed from the Diuell by anointing herſelf with oyle, into
which another Priest that prayed for her, had mingled his Teares.</q>
            <p>I think, of late daies our <hi>Romiſh Prieſts</hi> haue wept
too little, and laught too much: and that is the reaſon, we are peſtred
with more fiends, than friends. But when the ſword of iuſtice is drawn, and
inflicted according to the waight and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their deteſtable
deſignes, we ſhall, I hope, haue fewer of them come ouer. This Couey of
night-birds may ſhrowd themſelues warme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the gentle wings of their
<hi>holy Father</hi> at <hi>Rome.</hi> I am ſure, as yet they play the
<hi>Bats</hi> and <hi>Moles</hi> with ſome of our Countrey-men; either
trenching themſelues in the Mines of their Labyrinths at home, or masking in
their gold &amp; ſiluer abroad, in the faſhion of Rake-hels &amp; Ruffians.

<note place="margin">How to kenne or ſmell a Prieſt.</note>If,
about <hi>Bloomeſbury</hi> or <hi>Holborne,</hi> thou meet a good ſmug
Fellow in a gold-laced ſuit, a cloke lined thorow with veluet, one that hath
good ſtore of coin in his purſe, Rings on his fingers, a Watch in his 
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3148:29"/>pocket, it may be of ſome thirty-pound price, a very
broad-laced Band, a Stiletto by his ſide, a man at his heeles, willing (vpon
ſmall acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance) to intrude into thy company, and ſtill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring
further to inſinuate with thee; then take heed of a Ieſuite, of the prouder
ſort of Prieſts. This man hath vowed <hi>pouerty.</hi> Feare not to truſt
him with thy wife: he hath vowed alſo <hi>chaſtity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But are Prieſts <hi>teares</hi> ſo precious, that they are an
<hi>Antidote</hi> againſt the poiſon of <hi>Diuels?</hi> Oh yes: who knowes
not, that there is admirable power in a Prieſts <hi>breath,</hi> his
<hi>gloues,</hi> his <hi>hoſe,</hi> his <hi>girdle,</hi> his
<hi>ſhirts,</hi> to ſcortch the Diuell; in his <hi>Albe,</hi> his
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mice,</hi> his <hi>Maniple,</hi> and his <hi>Stole,</hi> to whip and
plague the Diuell? Or hath none read of the dreadfull power of <hi>Holy-water,
hallowed Candles, Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, Brimſtone,</hi> the <hi>Book of
Exorciſmes,</hi> and the <hi>holy potion,</hi> to ſcald, broil, and to
ſizle the Diuell? of the dreadfull power of the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> and
<hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the <hi>Altar,</hi> to torment the Diuell, and to make
him roar? If any think theſe ſtrange, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre him to a Book written by
D. <hi>Harſenet,</hi> now <hi>Biſhop of Norwich,</hi> the Title whereof I
haue ſet in the Margent:<note place="margin">A Declaration of egregious
Popiſh Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw the harts of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Subjects
from their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leageance, and from the truth of Chriſtian Religion, <hi>vid.
c.</hi> 14. 15. 16. 18 &amp; 20.</note> and you ſhall finde, that one
<hi>Father Edmunds, alias Weſton, F. Dibdale, F. Thomſon, F. Stemp, F.
Tyrrell, F. Dryland, F. Tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ce, F.
Sherwood, F. Winkefield, F. Mud, F. Dakins,</hi> and <hi>F. Bal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rd, Prieſts</hi> and
<hi>Ieſuites,</hi> haue ſtoutly and ſtrongly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed all this long
ſince. If the Book cannot ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily bee gotten, I wiſh it might bee
imprinted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, for that the Prieſts exorciſing power is 
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3148:30"/>there fully diſcouered: and I haue heard, that the moſt
of theſe Books which were formerly printed, were bought-vp by Papiſts, who
(no queſtion) took ſo much delight in reading them, that they burned as
many as they could poſſibly get of them. But, to acquaint you with the
ſtrange power of a <hi>Catholique Prieſts breath:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Plin. <hi>in hiſt.
nat.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Pliny</hi> in his <hi>Naturall Story,</hi> tels vs of
certain people, that doo <hi>anhelitu or is enecare homines,</hi> kill men with
the breath that comes from their mouthes. And <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> in the Comedy is
noted to bee of ſo ſtrong a breath, that hee had almoſt blowne downe the
young Gallant that ſtood in his way: but the <hi>Poets</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ouid. Virgil. Homer.</note> tell vs, that <hi>Hell hath a more
deadly breathing than all;</hi> ſo as if a Bird doo by chance flee ouer the
<hi>Stygian Floud,</hi> ſhee is quelled with the ſmell, and fals down
ſtark dead. Now, the company of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> for potency of
<hi>breath,</hi> doo put down <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, Leno, Hell,</hi> the <hi>Diuell</hi>
and all: for, the Diuell, who can well enough indure the lothſome odors and
euaporations of hell, is not able to indure the vapour iſſuing from the
mouth of a Prieſt; but had rather go to hell, than abide his ſmell. And
hence it is (I think), that, in their <hi>baptizing of children,</hi> the
<hi>Priest breathes</hi> and <hi>ſpets</hi> into the <hi>mouth</hi> of the
<hi>childe:</hi> which (no doubt) is very ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, eſpecially if the
<hi>priests lungs</hi> bee but a little vlcerated or pockified. One <hi>William
Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and <hi>Sarah Williams</hi> (as you ſhall reade in
<hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop Harſenet</hi>'s Book, page 71.) beeing
<hi>poſſeſſed,</hi> Trayfords <hi>Diuell rebounded at the dint of the
prieſts</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:3148:30"/>
               <hi>breath,</hi> and was glad to get him out
at <hi>Trayfords right eare, like a mouſe,</hi> rather than he would come out
jump againſt the <hi>prieſts</hi> mouth. 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ngus</hi> the Canoniſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs a rule, that if the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell be
ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, and will not obey the formidable exorciſme of the Prieſt, then
that the Prieſt ſhall <hi>os ſuum quamproxime ad energu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num admouere.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sarah
Williams lay paſt all ſenſe in a tranſe, being vtterly bereaued of all
her ſenſes at once: the prieſt no ſooner came neer her, but ſhe
diſcerned him by the ſmell.</hi> Was not this a jolly rank ſmell? Yea,
but this is but a flea-biting to the <hi>prieſts gloues, his hoſe, his
girdle, his ſhirts,</hi> which had in them a dreadfull power to burne out a
Diuell, nay, all the <hi>Diuels</hi> in the parties a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid
<hi>poſſeſſed.</hi> Which <hi>Diuels,</hi> becauſe the
<hi>prieſts</hi> knew ſo well their names, ſhall not heer go vnci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: 
<note place="margin">Page 181.</note>
               <hi>Lustie Dick, Killico, Hob,
Corner-cap, Puffe, Purre, Frateretto, Fliberdigibbet, Haberdicut, Coco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batto,
Maho, Kellicocam, Wilkin, Smolkin, luſtie iolly Ienkin, Portericho, Pudding
of Thame, Pour-dieu, Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iour, Motubizanto, Nur, Bernon, Delicate.</hi> The
chief of theſe Diuels, when one of the <hi>prieſts gloues</hi> was but put
vpon the <hi>poſſeſſed</hi>'s hands, durſt not abide, but was
ſcared, and went ſtraight away. One of the great <hi>Diuels</hi> was
ſlipt, ere he was aware, into <hi>Sarah Williams</hi> legge: 
<note place="margin">Page 81.</note>where finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf caught
within the <hi>Priests hoſe</hi> which ſhe had on, he plunges and tumbles
like a <hi>Salmon</hi> taken in a Net, and cries, <hi>Harro ho: out alas! pull
off, pull off: caſe the poore Diuell of his pain</hi> (oh, a goodly ginne to
catch a Woodcock withall). O but let me tell you of another trick, though not
ſo cleanly as I could wiſh. 
<note place="margin">Page 87.</note>One <hi>Fid</hi> (Landreſſe
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the <hi>Diuels in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate</hi>)
was waſhing a Buck of foule clothes: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which, was one of the
<hi>Prieſt-Exorciſts</hi> 
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:3148:31"/>ſhirts. The Diuell comes
ſneaking behinde her, trips vp her heeles, and pitcheth her on her hip. And
wot you why the Diuell played her this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannerly trick? Becauſe ſhe was
waſhing-out a foule ſhirt of one of the Prieſts, which afterward ſerued
to whip the Diuell out of one of the <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed.</hi> There are yet
other <hi>Anti-daemoniacks</hi> of ſpeciall account, which, in the
Diuell-hunting ſport, are in ſtead of little Beagles to fill vp the Cry.
And they are the <hi>Amice,</hi> the <hi>Albe,</hi> and the holy
<hi>Stole;</hi> very ſcorpions and whips indeed: and therefore beware,
Diuell. 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>page</hi> 89.</note>
               <hi>F. Edmunds</hi> no
ſooner laid the <hi>Amice</hi> vpon <hi>Sarah Williams</hi> her face, but a
ſpirit puffed at it, and could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to let it alone. The ſacred
<hi>Stole</hi> was but wound about anothers neck that was
<hi>poſſeſſed,</hi> and it ſo pent and begirt the Diuell, that hee
ſtared, fumed and fomed, as he had been ſtark mad; and, in the end, was
ſqueezed out with pure violence, as water out of a ſquirt. An heroicall
combate was performed between <hi>Maho,</hi> one of the diuels, and the
Prieſt, during ſeuen houres long. 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>page</hi> 90.</note>
               <hi>Maho</hi> the diuell
ſtood vpon his guard, would not come in. He was ſummoned by the Prieſt,
firſt, with <hi>Salue Regina,</hi> and <hi>Aue Maria;</hi> then with
<hi>Mengus</hi> club, with his whip, with <hi>Holy-water. Maho</hi> ſtood
out, till the Prieſt prepared himſelf to afflict him with the
<hi>Maniple:</hi> and then he came in, and yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to parley or dialogue with
the Prieſt in a milde and temperate voice. See the puiſſance of the
Catholique Romiſh Church, whoſe ſillieſt<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3148:31"/>rag hath
power to change the diuels roaring note, and to cauſe him to ſpeake in a
milde mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate key! <hi>Latet anguis in herba:</hi> a man would little
ſuſpect, when he meets with the <hi>Amice,</hi> the <hi>Stole,</hi> and the
<hi>Maniple,</hi> wound vp in a little casket, that there were ſuch black
hel-metall within them, to excoriate and lancinate a diuell.<note place="margin">All theſe tricks and many more were acted at <hi>Denham</hi> in
<hi>Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hamſhire,</hi> about the yeer 1590.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But I conclude: <hi>Niſi naenijs, tricis, et puppis vſa
eſſet Roma, poenas iam diu dediſſet:</hi> If it were not for puppets,
apes-faces, and gawdes, with which <hi>Rome</hi> allures, maskes, and
diſguiſes the poore ſilly people, ſhee had long ſince ſung the
dolefull Song mentioned in holy Writ; <hi>Deſolatione mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deſolata eſt, et turpitudo eius
gentibus reuelata;</hi> that is, <hi>ſhee had bin cleane deſolate, and her
turpitude had beene opened to the eyes of all the world.</hi> As for all the
tricks and iuggling ſhifts (ſo often diſcouered) which the
<hi>Prieſts,</hi> theſe <hi>Exorciſts, vſe;</hi> the
<hi>Exorciſt</hi> driuing the <hi>Diuell</hi> within the liſts of the
<hi>poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed body</hi> (with Come aloft, <hi>Iack-an-apes</hi>) from
one part to another: to what end doe all theſe their dealings tend, but to
this proiect, that the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s-by may be perſwaded of ſome point of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> or of
the <hi>Prieſts power ouer the Diuels?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any Chriſtian in theſe daies hath been true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and really
poſſeſſed by the Diuell, and if the Romiſh Prieſts haue truely
ſuch a ſcourging power to whip out Diuels, why vſe they it not
effectually when moſt need is? For example
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> There was one M. <hi>Blewet,</hi>
a man of great reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes, and one M. <hi>Fowell,</hi> a man no leſſe
famou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3148:32"/>both of which either were or ſeemed to bee
indiuelled. How often had they beene <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orcized</hi> in this Kingdom, by
<hi>Francis Kemp,</hi> by <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip Woodward,</hi> by <hi>F. Edmunds,</hi> by
<hi>F. Campian,</hi> by <hi>F. Sherwin,</hi> by <hi>F. Hil,</hi> by <hi>F.
Walpool,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers others, but eſpecially, <hi>F. Collington,</hi> and
<hi>F. Warmington,</hi> who often promiſed, they would make the Diuell
ſpeake in M. <hi>Blewet,</hi> and M. <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</hi> But as thoſe two had
many ſweating com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates heere in <hi>England,</hi> ſo had they tormentings
at <hi>Loretto, Sichem, Lile, Louaine, Doway,</hi> &amp; elſwhere beyond the
<hi>Seas;</hi> and all the conſolation which they found, was to returne
worſe, and farther from hope of deliuerance, then when they went. The
Popiſh <hi>ſanctuaries</hi> rather added ſtrength to the diuels. And yet
our <hi>Popiſh Thraſonical Prieſts</hi> will brag &amp; boaſt, that
they can toſſe a diuell like <hi>a Tennis-ball,</hi> or <hi>a Dog</hi> in
<hi>a blanket;</hi> whereat they are very nimble, eſpecially in a
poſſeſſed woman, in whoſe body they can canuas a diuell by
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trectation and certaine inchanting nips, making him ferret vp and downe,
from tongue to toe, from toe back againe to finger. Oh the formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable magicall
power of ſacred anointed hands, not onely infuſing chaſtity but alſo
ſanctity by their touch!</p>
            <p>I could heere ſet foorth another Theatre of their
<hi>Exorciſing</hi> plots and attempts, to weet, their practiſing with
<hi>Grace Sowrebuts</hi> of <hi>Salmisburie,</hi> in the County of
<hi>Lancaſter;</hi> whom one <hi>Thomſon, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias Southworth, a Priest,</hi>
cauſed to accuſe <hi>Iennet</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:3148:32"/>
               <hi>Bierly, Helen
Bierly,</hi> and <hi>Iane Southworth,</hi> (the one of them her Grand-mother)
of <hi>Witchcraft,</hi> of the killing of the childe of <hi>Thomas
Walſhman,</hi> with a Naile in the Nauill, the boyling, eating and oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
thereby to tranſ-forme themſelues into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſhapes: 
<note place="margin">This was done about 14. yeers ago.</note>all
which, at the <hi>Aſsiſes</hi> holden at <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> prooued to
be falſe; and the ſaid <hi>Grace Sowrebuts</hi> confeſſed, that ſhe
was perſwaded and counſelled to accuſe the ſaid parties of
<hi>Witchcraft,</hi> by M. <hi>Thomſon, alias,</hi> M. <hi>Chriſtopher
Southworth a Prieſt,</hi> who comploted this, to gaine to himſelfe ſome
credit by exorciſing, or vnwitching her. This confeſſion of <hi>Grace
Sowrebuts,</hi> with the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of others, who diſcouered the Prieſts
impious dealings, was taken before <hi>William Leigh,</hi> Batchelor in
Diuinity, and <hi>Edward Chiſnall</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, two of his Maieſties
Iuſtices of peace in that County.<note place="margin">The Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations were
put ſince in print by <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Pots,</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</note> Sure, theſe
iuggling exorciſmes are but ordinary with Prieſts and Ieſuites: but
ſuch a malicious and bloudy proiect of ſuborna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, muſt bee a
maſter-trick of ſome ſublimed ſpirit, fit to inſtruct a nouice
<hi>Aſſaſsine,</hi> and to read a Lecture in the Ieſuites dark chamber
of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Boy of <hi>Bilſon.</hi>
               </note>For the
next vnmasking of our <hi>Mirabilaries.</hi> I might adde the
<hi>Narration</hi> of certaine <hi>Prieſts,</hi> practiſing with the
<hi>Boy of Bilſon. Anno</hi> 1621. whoſe name was <hi>William Perry,</hi>
Sonne of <hi>Tho. Perry of Bilſon,</hi> in the County of <hi>Stafford.</hi>
But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there hath beene ſo lately a true diſcouery of the notorious
Impoſtures of certaine <hi>Romiſh</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:3148:33"/>
               <hi>Prieſts,</hi> in their pretended Exorciſme or expulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of
the diuell out of the ſaid young Boy; I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre you to M. <hi>Rich.
Baddeley</hi> his book vpon that occaſion written: and I intreat you to
conſider, whether they deſerue not the reputation of the rareſt
Mounte-banks of theſe times. <hi>Quam falſa dicendo voluptatem ceperint,
eandem vera legendo et audiendo amittant.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In
praeſat. lib. praedict.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Two Maids poſſeſt with the Virgin
<hi>Mary, Michael</hi> the Arch-An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, &amp;c.</note>About ſome ſeuen
yeeres ſince, <hi>two Catholique Maids,</hi> forſooth, the one called
<hi>Mary,</hi> the other <hi>Amye,</hi> reſorting to the <hi>Gatehouſe</hi>
in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> took ſuch benefit by the Prieſts
conuerſation with them, beeing ſometimes ſequeſtred from all the world
beſides, that they were caſt into <hi>extaticall</hi> raptures, and
<hi>poſſeſſed,</hi> not with <hi>Diuels,</hi> as the vulgar ſort of
thoſe that vndergoe the <hi>Prieſts</hi> hands, but with heauenly and
glorious gueſts, pretended to enter into them, and inhabit them, to the great
admiration of the ſtupid, gullifyed, <hi>Romanizing</hi> beholders, and to
the no ſmall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne of the <hi>Spirituall Fathers</hi> then preſent;
<hi>F. Benet, F. Aſton, F. Palmer, F. Hanz.</hi> In very deed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law, they were
ſomtimes <hi>poſſeſt</hi> with the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> other-while
with Saint <hi>Michael</hi> the Arch-Angell, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the
<hi>Baptiſt,</hi> M. <hi>Molineux</hi> the Martyr, and M. <hi>Roberts</hi>
the Martyr,<note place="margin">Two Tiburn-martyrs.</note> and diuers other
aſwell Maſculine as Feminine Saints; and, in the name of theſe
<hi>Saints,</hi> did giue <hi>bleſsings</hi> to ſuch as were preſent. The
ſubſtance of which narration hath been, vpon the Examination of one of
their <hi>Exorciſts,</hi> confeſſed. Yet when this<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3148:33"/>was
blowne abroad, and beganne to breed ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall vnto the <hi>Catholick
cauſe,</hi> one of the maides gaue-ouer her pretended gueſt, and the other
was ſecretly conueyed away.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">One <hi>Hanz, alias, Hance</hi>
poſſeſſed with the bleſſed Trinity.</note>One of the forenamed
Prieſts calling himſelf <hi>Edward Hanz, alias, Hance,</hi> borne at
<hi>Lutterworth</hi> in <hi>Leiceſterſhire,</hi> had a trick beyond all his
fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, and durſt aſpire ſo high, as to pretend himſelfe to bee
caſt into a deepe admirable exta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and to bee corporally
<hi>poſſeſſed (horreſco refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens) with the bleſſed
Trinitie.</hi> Neither was hee more abominably knauiſh in this his
<hi>Impuden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi> then ſome of his owne Coat, who were then blockiſhly
fooliſh in their <hi>credulity.</hi> For ſome of them, when hee acted this
his <hi>Trinitarian rapture</hi> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me and kneeled to him, bringing <hi>Oblations tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plici
numero,</hi> to preſent vnto the <hi>Trinity,</hi> inhabiting this
Mounte-banke. Among which gifts preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by theſe <hi>Lozels,</hi> one
was <hi>gold-coine,</hi> an oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on neuer vnacceptable to thoſe that
pretend <hi>creare Creatorem.</hi> That it is no fiction in mee to relate this
their fiction, may appeare by the <hi>Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination</hi> of the ſaid
<hi>Hanz</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aken, <hi>Iulij</hi>
5. 1616. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the L. Arcbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the LL. BB. of
<hi>London, Lincolne, Rocheſter, Litchfield,</hi> the Deane of
<hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and Sir <hi>W. Bird,</hi> D. of the Law: before whom
he denieth not ſuch his <hi>rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and poſſeſsion.</hi> For beeing
then demanded, whether hee euer took on him to bee 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verbatim,</hi> out of the
Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note>
               <hi>poſſeſſed with the bleſſed Trinity,</hi>
ſaying of himſelfe, <hi>I God the Father, that made the world; I God the
Sonne, <pb n="56" facs="tcp:3148:34"/>that redeemed the world; I God the holy Ghoſt,
that ſanctified the world, the glorious, bleſſed and vndiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Trinity,
doe giue you my bleſsing, and doe command you to adore mee:</hi> And beeing
further asked, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome that were preſent, did not <hi>adore him,</hi>
and ſome other <hi>refuſed:</hi> hee anſwered, 
<note place="margin">This <hi>Hans</hi> with his cogging tranſe, is
ſo bold and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous, as to allude vnto S. <hi>Pauls</hi> rapture, 2
Cor. 12.3</note>
               <hi>That once or twice when hee was about thoſe actions, or
in the</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terim <hi>of them, he was in a tranſe, and his ſoule did
ſee very ſupernaturall and admirable ioyes: and then whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God Almighty
or an Angell (hee will not med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with it, but referreth it to God Almighty
and his Church) ſpake in the name of God and the bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and
gaue a Bleſsing, and that himſelfe at thoſe times, had no power in
himſelfe, but that the Organs of his body were vſed to a ſupernaturall
purpoſe, and by a diuine or ſupernaturall cauſe: And as God did cauſe
the Aire to ſpeak, in giuing downe the Law, ſaying,</hi> I AM THE LORD THY
GOD; <hi>and did cauſe</hi> Balaams <hi>Aſſe to vtter words: ſo hee
might cauſe the Organs of this Examinates body, to ſpeak as beſt
pleaſed the will of his diuine Maieſty: and the truth of the whole action,
hee doth referre to God Almighty and his Church. And he doth ſay fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for
his part, that no humane perſon whatſoeuer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing can vſe the Name of
the bleſſed Trinity; ſaying,</hi> I the bleſſed Trinity bleſſe
you, <hi>without ſinne, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe God almighty doo take the creature, and
ſpeake in him: and then it is Gods owne word, and not the word of the party.
But touching adoration, there was no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of it, to his remembrance:
and if any did it, it was no more than due to the eternall Trinity, who may be
adored in all places.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:3148:34"/>This impoſture, though neuer ſo odious and
blaſphemous, yet flew abroad, and was foſtered as a true Miracle. For
confirmation whereof, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port was added, that this holy Prieſt thus
poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by the <hi>Trinity, walking vp and down the ſtreets daily
amongst the Hereticks, yet none of them had the power to apprehend or lay hands
on him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I could acquaint you with other his horrible and ſacrilegious
impieties: but let this ſuffice. It was foretold by Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> that
their adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Mother ſhould haue <hi>her mouth full of
blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 13.6.</note>which, to her ſhame,
wee doo now obſerue. And according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>The ſpirit
ſpeaketh expreſly, that in the latter times, ſome ſhall depart from the
faith, giuing heed to ſeducing ſpirits, and doctrines of diuels, ſpeaking
lies in hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, hauing their conſciences ſeared with an hot
iron:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.1,2,3.</note> which beeing the propertie
of falſe prophets, it is more then manifeſt, who are ſpecified,
eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if wee ponder thoſe words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Such ſhould
forbid marriage, and command men to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from meats, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To theſe two laſt blaſphemies, it will not bee amiſſe to
adde what our <hi>Papiſts</hi> report of <hi>Katharine</hi> of
<hi>Sienna.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In vit. Sanct.</hi> Katharin <hi>de
Sienna.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>She</hi> (forſooth) and <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> by
an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable kinde of permutation, <hi>did enterchange their hearts;</hi> ſo
that <hi>Chriſt</hi> had <hi>the heart of Katharine;</hi> and
<hi>Katharine,</hi> that of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Oh you ignorant and
deſperately-ſuperſtitious <hi>Pontificians,</hi> who iuſtifie this
Fable! Obſerue you not? vnderſtand you not, that this miraculous chaffering
of hearts <pb n="58" facs="tcp:3148:35"/>ſubuerteth a very Principle of Chriſtian
Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (receiued alſo by your ſelues) which is, that <hi>quod Chriſtus
ſemel aſſumpſit, nunquam dimiſit,</hi> what Chriſt did once
aſſume (to weet, by hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaticall vnion) he neuer left the ſame.</p>
            <p>I cannot by the way omit a fantaſticall relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the
<hi>Papiſts,</hi> which I read in <hi>Baronius,</hi> how the Virgin <hi>Mary
viſited Fulbert</hi> in his ſicknes, and <hi>gaue him her breaſts to
ſuck,</hi> much comforting him thereby.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Baron.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1028. <hi>ff.</hi>
5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I beleeue, there eſcaped at that time ſome drops of milk from
<hi>Fulbertus</hi> his lips, hee beeing not accuſtomed to ſuck, and thoſe
are they which are kept in a ſiluer image of the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> in her
Church at <hi>Rhemes,</hi> and are there worſhipped.</p>
            <p>There was of late, <hi>viz. an.</hi> 1621. one impriſoned either
in the <hi>Gate-houſe</hi> or <hi>New-priſon,</hi> who cald himſelf
<hi>Newton:</hi> he pretended, he had a <hi>Viſion</hi> by night of the
<hi>Virgin Mary</hi> appearing vnto him, and ſaying, <hi>Newton, ſee that
thou doo not take the oath of alleageance.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi>
High-Commiſſion Records.</note> And being of this publiquely exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and
asked, How he knew it to be the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> which appeared? he
anſwered, <hi>I knew it was ſhee: for, ſhe appeared vnto me in the forme
of her Aſſumption.</hi> Of what nature that idle Viſion was, the Reader
may finde in M. <hi>Widrington,</hi> who han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleth the ſame, and doth in part
diſcouer the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity thereof. A pretty Argument this was againſt taking the
<hi>Oath.</hi> Since I heard thereof, I asked a Prieſt,<note place="margin">M.
<hi>Rich.</hi>
               </note> what he thought of this viſion of <hi>Newton</hi>'s.
Hee told mee, that <hi>This</hi> Newton <hi>was a very holy</hi> 
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:3148:35"/>
               <hi>man, and hath had other viſions beſides that: which
if he ſhould repeat, would make a man tremble and quake. Hereticks</hi>
(quoth he) <hi>haue no ſuch viſions &amp; heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apparitions.</hi> I
knowe not whom he meant by the word <hi>Hereticks:</hi> but if he mean vs
<hi>Protestants,</hi> who haue more reaſon to inuert the phraſe vpon them;
ſure, we are not ſuch liſtners to miracles. <hi>Prodigia nulla facimus:
ſigna nulla edimus:</hi> we work no wonders: wee ſhew no viſions, as
<hi>Acoſta</hi> a Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite of theirs once aſſeuerantly deliuered.<note place="margin">Acoſt. <hi>Ieſ. de ſalut. Indor.</hi> l 4</note>
            </p>
            <p>Our Sauiour Chriſt himſelf (as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
obſerueth)<note place="margin">Aug. <hi>Tract.</hi> 13 <hi>in</hi> Ioh.
3</note> 
               <hi>hath giuen vs a caution against theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle-mongers; willing
vs to take heed, that we be not deceiued.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark
13.5</note> Yea, their owne <hi>Preacher Stella</hi> (whom of late time they
haue gelt, as they doo all other their Writers, when they meet with any thing
that makes not for their turn) entring into this contemplation, taught
publiquely, that <hi>Miracles now would rather be an hinderance vnto
faith.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stel. <hi>in</hi> Luc. 11</note>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Katharine de Bus,</hi> dwelling in the City of <hi>Lile,</hi>
in the County of <hi>Flanders,</hi> in the yeere 1602. was poſſeſſed of
the Diuell; inſomuch that ſhee could bee ſcarce a quarter of an houre in
peace, without beeing ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed vpon and troubled by the enemie: which made her
ſpeake (to the purpoſe) diuers ſorts of Languages; as, Hebrew, Greeke,
and Latine. When they came neere vnto her with the bleſſed Sacrament of the
Altar, ſhee writhed and wreſted her ſelfe ſtrangely, both with her
leggs, armes, and back, gnaſhing her teeth, and grizly drawing of her mouth.
The parents of this wench la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3148:36"/>ſo much, that ſhee
was diuers times exorciſed, ſometimes by certaine Fathers of the order of
the Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chins, ſometimes by other Prieſts: vnto whom the wicked Spirits
anſwered in diuers Languages, confeſsing at that time, that they were
ſeuen in number. They ſpake diuers iniurious things, and told the faults of
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers that were preſent. No meanes could bee vſed for the caſting out
of theſe wicked Fiends, till there was found a man that was come from
<hi>Mountague,</hi> and had brought with him a piece of the Oke of our Ladie.
Whereupon, one Sir <hi>Silueſter Dennys,</hi> who came to ſee her, took the
ſaid piece, and made the Patient to eat it: and immediatly after ſhee had
ſwallowed it, the enemy (who called himſelfe <hi>Houilliu Clicquet</hi> and
<hi>Clinquart</hi>) ſhewed himſelfe in her throat; crying out, that he
ſcorched and burned, becauſe of the wood which was eaten: and hee added,
that he was compelled to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and that there remained in her as yet three.
And beeing demanded, by whoſe merit and interceſsion hee was to depart; The
wicked ſpirit anſwered, Of <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Mountague.</hi> Afterwards,
beeing demanded, what ſigne he would giue of his departure, he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaid, He would burſt a glaſſe
of the Church-window. And im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after, two of them departed with the
ſaid ſigne of burſting the glaſſe; and the third, ſaying that hee
was the laſt of tenne, cryed out (in going foorth) with aloud voice, <hi>Viue
N. Dame de Mountague, qui nous faict ſortir:</hi> Honour bee to our Lady of
<hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tague,</hi> who maketh vs to depart. And from that day afterwards, the
ſaid <hi>Katharine</hi> remained whole and perfectly free from the
poſſeſsion and vexation of the <pb n="61" facs="tcp:3148:36"/>enemie, inioying
al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her limmes and ſenſes as
freely as euer ſhee did before: <hi>In lib. intit.</hi> Miracles lately
wrought by the interceſsion of the glorious Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> at
<hi>Mountague;</hi> and tranſlated out of the French into Engliſh, by
<hi>Rob. Chambers,</hi> Prieſt, page 209. 210. et ſeq.</q>
            <p>This buzzing relation, penned and publiſhed by the Prieſts
themſelues, is ſuteable and (in a ſort) paralell to that which
<hi>Brerely</hi> tells vs of diuers who were <hi>diſpoſſeſſed of
Diuels, by kiſsing of the Altar and the Priests vesture.</hi> But I will cap
this tale with a freſh-bleeding new Story, fetcht not farre without the
walles of London.</p>
            <p>A certaine <hi>Catholicke collapſed Ladie</hi> (whoſe name I
ſpare, for the reſpect I beare to her beſt friends) about ſome two or
three yeeres ſince, departed from her husband (yet liuing) and went ouer to
<hi>Bruxels,</hi> and was admitted into the order of <hi>Nunnerie,</hi> I meane
a <hi>Nunne</hi> at large, one of the vncloiſtred ſiſters of <hi>the
order</hi> of <hi>Saint Clare,</hi> and there ſhee remained a while, till
there appeared in her ſome paſſion incompatible with <hi>Nunſhip.</hi>
Shee came ouer into <hi>England</hi> a companion with a <hi>religious
Ieſuite,</hi> ſince of great note, <hi>F. D.</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining afterwards
an inlarged <hi>Nunne</hi> in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, was (as it ſeemeth) more viſibly
taken with a diſeaſe befalling that ſexe, called <hi>flatus
vterinus:</hi> and thereupon, that this matter might bee car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the more
cleanely, it was giuen out, that ſhee was poſſeſſed with an euill
ſpirit, which did make<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3148:37"/>her belly to ſwell like a woman
with child. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is, many were deluded by this occaſion: and the
practice of the Prieſts to hide her ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh, and gull poore people, was
lewd and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable. For a certaine Ieſuite<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.
T.</hi>
               </note> (whom I could alſo name, being a ſmug, ſpruce,
liquoriſh, young fellow, a fit man to bee called <hi>Father</hi> (forſooth)
at euery word, &amp; of no high ſtature; and ſo, fit to be a diſguiſed
<hi>Olympio,</hi> to act the part of <hi>Caſina</hi> in <hi>Plautus,</hi> or
to act a womanized <hi>Chaerea</hi> in <hi>Terence</hi> his <hi>Eunuchus</hi>)
put on the Ladies or ſuch like wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſh apparel, with a Vaile ouer his
face: &amp; that ſome found Ignaro's about the Towne might be perſwaded of
the Prieſts power <hi>for the caſting out of Diuels,</hi> they were
ſuffred to come to her cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, where were two other Ieſuites<note place="margin">One of theſe, namely, <hi>F. D.</hi> about halfe a yeare after,
was a chiefe Actor in a true lamentable Tragedy, yet memorable by a
Downfall.</note> (prouided for the purpoſe, to act their parts in this
Comedie); who no ſooner fell to their prayers, and began to vſe their
exorcizing ſpels, but thereupon the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Ladie began to vtter her
mind both in <hi>Italian, Latin</hi> and <hi>Greeke:</hi> which much
aſtoniſhed the ſtanders by, they little dreaming of this deceit. Neither
was this all: I will yet proceed farther in this ſo comicall a Narration.</p>
            <p>It was wont, when an Interlude was to bee acted in a Countrey
Towne, the firſt queſtion that an Hob-naile Spectator made, before hee
would pay his penny to goe in, was, <hi>Whether there bee a Diuell and a Foole
in the play?</hi> And if the Foole get vpon the Diuels backe, and beate him
with his Cox-combe till hee roare, the play is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat.<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3148:37"/>Here is Foole vpon Foole, but <hi>extra ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,</hi> off from the
Stage; the gaping, admiring, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing Spectators. But to make this pageant
compleat, this diſguiſed Diuel muſt roare; &amp; that was, by the
bringing the conſecrated <hi>Hoſt</hi> in a <hi>Pix,</hi> and applying it
vnder the head of this <hi>Shee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knaue-Ieſuite, or Hee-lubberly Lady.</hi>
Then his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel-ſhip <hi>raues</hi> and <hi>ſtruggles,</hi> as if hee would
rather goe to hell againe, then indure the tormenting preſence of the
<hi>Holy Pix.</hi> Diuers other feats were performed vpon this occaſion,
which I will ſpare to declare, till I receiue <hi>Command</hi> on the one
ſide, or <hi>Challenge</hi> on the other.</p>
            <p>Whether ſhe euer heard of her ſelfe thus acted in her
abſence, I know not, but ſure I haue heard from a credible author, that
ſhe was actiue, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſſiue in one tragical part of this
<hi>Mummery;</hi> which (mee thinks) ſhee ſhould rather ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had
performed it for her. Forſooth, theſe <hi>Medicinall Diuel-purgers</hi>
were not to ſeeke for the deuice of the <hi>conſecrated potion</hi> (in
imitation of that which was giuen to <hi>Sarah Williams</hi> at
<hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> before-mentioned): this <hi>potion</hi> muſt make her
<hi>vomit vp</hi> no leſſe then <hi>ſeuen Diuels:</hi> and to that end,
ſhee was let downe into a darke roome, and there ſhut vp for a time without
light; and, after the operation of this Diuel-ſcowring vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, light was
let-in, and ſeuen <hi>Todes</hi> ſhewed to her in the place, as regorged by
her, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no leſſe then (doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leſſe) dreadfull Diuels.</p>
            <p>This laſt circumſtance I doe not auerre vpon 
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3148:38"/>knowledge, as acted by them; but rather think it giuen-out
by the party and others, to pretend, that ſome great miracles haue been
wrought in her, or by her, that ſhe might haue the better pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to haue
been reſembled vnto <hi>Mary Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> out of whom <hi>ſeuen Diuels
were cast.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Leauing it then <hi>in medio,</hi> till I receiue better
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; yet ſure I am, <hi>ſhee</hi> carrieth the name of <hi>working
miracles.</hi> And indeed well may it bee ſo ſaid, that <hi>ſhee</hi> and
her <hi>Copeſ-mates</hi> the <hi>Prieſts</hi> do work miracles: for, to my
vnderſtanding, it is little leſſe than a miracle, that any of our Nation,
vncapable of <hi>Bedlam</hi> or a <hi>Bable,</hi> ſhould be ſtricken with
ſuch ſtupidity, as to beleeue in theſe <hi>Iugglers</hi> and <hi>Romiſh
Mounte-banks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I ſhould heer recount all the <hi>Lies</hi> and
<hi>Tales</hi> of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> concerning the multitudes that haue been
diſpoſſeſſed of Diuels, by the help of a whole Beuy of Ladies; Our
<hi>Lady</hi> of <hi>Mountague,</hi> our <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> of <hi>Loretto,</hi>
our <hi>Lady</hi> of <hi>Hales,</hi> and our <hi>Lady</hi> of <hi>Sienna:</hi>
no reaſonable Volume would receiue or containe them. I referre him that would
ſpend idle time in idle fables, to <hi>Rob. Chambers</hi> his book
before-cited, and to <hi>T. P.</hi> his book intituled, <hi>The History of our
bleſſed Lady of Loretto,</hi> and to <hi>Lipſius</hi> his dotages of our
<hi>Lady</hi> of <hi>Hales,</hi> and to <hi>I. Heigham</hi> his book intituled,
<hi>The Lady of Sienna:</hi> and you will need no other Regiſter of their
Impoſtures, no <hi>golden Legend.</hi> Doting <hi>Metaphrastes,</hi> fabulous
<hi>Lippoman,</hi> lying and voraginous <hi>Iacobus,</hi> ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
<hi>Antonine,</hi> confuſe <hi>Vincentius,</hi> haue ſo cloyed 
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3148:38"/>the <hi>dwellers vpon earth</hi> with deluſions and lies,
that (for very ſhame) the Papiſts haue exploded and pared out of their
<hi>Porteſſes</hi> and <hi>Breuiaries</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and ſundry of their
fabulous Hiſtories, being indeed forced thereunto by the deriſions &amp;
out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries of Chriſtians againſt them. Yea, <hi>Claudius Eſpencae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> (one of their owne) telles vs,<note place="margin">Eſpenc. <hi>in</hi> 2 <hi>ad</hi> Tim. <hi>et digreſ. l.
c.</hi> 1. 11.</note> that their <hi>Legends</hi> and <hi>Porteſſes</hi>
were as full of idle vanities, as any Stables could be full of dung. <hi>What
fruit was there in thoſe things, wherof you are now aſhamed?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.11</note>
            </p>
            <p>Who (me thinks) could bee ſo bewitched, as be born in hand, that
<hi>A houſe was carried in the aire from</hi> Paleſtina <hi>to</hi>
Loretto;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>T. P.</hi> page 40.</note> that <hi>a Dalmatian
Priest</hi> comming many miles to <hi>Loretto,</hi> and carrying vp with his
hand his bowels quite pulled out of his belly, by one onely praier to our Lady
there, was inſtantly healed;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>T. P.</hi> page 181. 182.
This is as true, as was our <hi>Dalmatian ventrioſus Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus
Amonius.</hi>
               </note> that a blockiſh Image in a wall, doth work as high
miracles, as euer were perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the eternall Sonne of God; that 
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Ful. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>droſ. Naucler.
Coſterum.</note>Saint <hi>Francis</hi> had the prints of our Sauiours wounds;
that the two <hi>Tails</hi> of our Sauiours <hi>Aſſe,</hi> the 
<note n="g" place="margin">S. <hi>Iohn Baptis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> head ſhewed both at <hi>Ami<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> and at <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </note>two
<hi>heads</hi> of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptist,</hi> the <hi>milk of our
bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lady, are this day to bee ſeen;</hi> that at the great 
<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Franc-Sales</hi> in his introduct. to
a deuout life <hi>Fitz-Simon.</hi>
               </note>Lake of <hi>Vister,</hi> Saint
<hi>Patrick</hi> (who chaſed all the venome out of <hi>Ireland</hi>) is one
day by the <hi>Prieſts</hi> yet viſible, and that 
<note n="*" place="margin">As <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> had with the nymph <hi>Aeg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note>
               <hi>they haue then conference with him;</hi> beſide,
that there is a wonder-working <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory</hi> of his; that a 
<note n="*" place="margin">A Carmelite
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tting, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by all the Prieſts now in
<hi>London:</hi> and one of them ſwore to me, that hee ſaw
it.</note>
               <hi>Carmelit</hi> came lately to <hi>Paris,</hi> and there ſaying
Maſſe, euery day, at the eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>conſecrated
Hoſt,</hi> himſelf was ſtill eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or hoiſed on cock-horſe into
the aire; that <hi>F.</hi> 
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:3148:39"/> 
               <hi>Steuens</hi> a
<hi>Prieſt</hi> (now in <hi>London</hi>) hath a <hi>Croſſe,</hi>
whereunto are affixed ſome Reliques of a dead Martyr, one M.
<hi>Maxfield:</hi> which Croſſe beeing ſtolne from him, and carried one
day almoſt fifty miles (as was known), the night following, came back of its
owne accord, and hee found it in the morning vnder his beds head:<note place="margin">If any man, being 50 miles from London, want an Hack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to carry
him back, let him hire F. <hi>Steuens</hi> gallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Croſſe.</note> which
Croſſe, ſurely, muſt bee a kinne to a Stone in <hi>Angleſey,</hi>
reported to be of that property, that how-farre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer a man carried it in
the day, it would return of it ſelf at night into the Iland; that the very
ſight of <hi>Garnets ſtraw</hi> hath made (at leaſt) fiue hundred in our
Kingdome become good <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> the
true Chriſtian Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick, written by <hi>I Heigham.</hi>
               </note> which if it
be true, I ſee no reaſon, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Threſher in <hi>England</hi>
ſhould become a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſt,</hi> becauſe they deale with ſtrawes,
which haue as perfect an <hi>effigies</hi> of <hi>F. Garnet,</hi> as any other
ſtraw without cquiuocation euer yet had; that M. <hi>Gennings</hi> executed
at <hi>Tiburn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> a Book in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit. The life
&amp; death of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund Gennings,</hi> page 86. </note> his belly beeing
opened, his bowels cut out, and his heart in the Executioners hand, yet the
<hi>Martyr</hi> cryed out, <hi>Sancte</hi> Gregori, <hi>ora pro me;</hi> Holy
<hi>Gregory,</hi> pray for me; that the ſame mans <hi>holy anointed
Thumb,</hi> beeing touched by a <hi>Virgin</hi> after his death, of it ſelf
came off, bone and fleſh, from the reſt of the hand;<note place="margin">Page
93. A Tale of <hi>Tom Thumb.</hi>
               </note> that when one M. <hi>Dakins</hi> a
<hi>Prieſt,</hi> executed at <hi>Tiburn,</hi> was a-dying,<note place="margin">Heigham, <hi>vt ſup. pag.</hi> 146.</note> a certain <hi>Virgin,
a kinſwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of his,</hi> though many miles remote, longing after ſome of
the Martyrs fleſh, ſhe not knowing how to obtain her deſire, yet being
full of faith, one of M. <hi>Dakins</hi> holy <hi>toes</hi> did miraculouſly
yield <pb n="67" facs="tcp:3148:39"/>it ſelf into her virginal hands;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>on</hi>
prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth, that he heard him ſpeak the ſame, <hi>vid. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of miracles, page 25.</note>
that <hi>Robert Parſons</hi> could make the Diuell ſpeak in any
<hi>Engliſh Biſhop</hi> or Heretick whomſoeuer; that <hi>Robert
Parſons</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing apprehended by a <hi>Purſuiuant</hi> at
<hi>Norwich</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> and put into a chamber faſt bolted
and locked vpon him, the dore did three times toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miraculouſly and of
its owne accord flee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>R. Parſons</hi> a pick-lock
equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocator.</note> that one <hi>F. Scroop</hi> a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> being in
a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans houſe in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> and certain Purſuiuants
coming to ſearch for him, notwithſtanding hee was in the midſt of the
Roum with them, yet he became inuiſible to the ſaid Searchers;<note place="margin">I think, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times viſible gold
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> make a man inuiſible</note>
that one <hi>Katharine Riland</hi> within the City of <hi>London,</hi> with
eating one bit of fleſh forbidden by her ghoſtly Father, was inſtantly
choked;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>G.A.P.</hi> in his book called, The rules of
obedience, page 12. <hi>G.A P.</hi> page 41</note> that one <hi>Thomas
Vincent</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> ſcoffing at a Prieſt ſaying M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſs, forthwith fell mad, and, for many
daies after, was heard pronounce no other words but theſe, <hi>O holy
Prieſt, O holy Maſſe;</hi> that old <hi>F. Chambers</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the
confeſſion of a <hi>Nun</hi> at <hi>Bruxels,</hi> her name M.
<hi>Stan,</hi> ſhe was me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amorphoſed, and ſeemed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him <hi>a flame of fire;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> a Prieſt in <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
that whenſoeuer a certaine Prieſt put his finger nigh <hi>Sauerius</hi> his
heart, there iſſued out bloud and water;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſel</hi> vit <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> c.</hi> 4.</note> that <hi>Holy
Father</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip Nerius, <hi>vpon a certain night as hee was walking, and
falling into a certain ditch, was preſently caught by the haires of his head
by an Angell, and ſo deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bar. <hi>in an.</hi>
1550</note> that an Image was crucified at <hi>Beritum,</hi> and did bleed;
that the diuell held both S. <hi>Edmunds</hi> his hands, that he could not make
the ſigne of the Croſſe;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in his proteſt. page 162.</note> that M.
<hi>Chriſtopher Cuſake,</hi> an <hi>Iriſh Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite,</hi> 
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:3148:40"/>had a <hi>Crucifix</hi> which could ſpeak?</p>
            <p>Are theſe graceleſſe ſaltleſſe gulleries, either to be
beleeued or countenanced? Is it poſſible, that men of wit, vnderſtanding
and ſpirit, ſhould bee intoxicated and carried away with ſuch muddy
deuices; the end of which is, <hi>non ethnicos conuertendi, ſed ipſos
euertendi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. <hi>de praeſcr. verſ.
haereticos.</hi>
               </note> not to conuert and bring any vnto the knowledge of the
truth, but rather to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> make them wallow in the mire and ſink of errour;
in which themſelues haue long ſtuck faſt? And by reading of all which you
may finde, that the Diuell hath no greater cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, nor preuaileable art, then
to ſupport the Romiſh Religion by ſuch palpable, groſſe, filthy and
idle inuentions. What is there in them (for the moſt part) more then in the
Poeticall fiction of the <hi>Gods;</hi> the Fables of <hi>Homer, Herodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,
Ouid, Bocace,</hi> and the reſt? All is but the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of lying tongues,
the preſumption &amp; brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of Inchanters, and the ceremonies of
<hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurers, Pythoniſts &amp; Arts-masters</hi> in Incantations: againſt
whom the Poets themſelues had many inuectiues, and condemned the Prieſts of
that time, as we do the <hi>Friers</hi> of this Age: as
<hi>Euripides,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eurip. Ion.</note> 
               <q> 
                  <l>Hei mihi! verſipelles vt homines ſemper odi,</l> 
                  <l>qui componentes iniuſta, deinde fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udes adornant.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The examples before-recited, ſhew the collu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions the
Prieſts vſe, vpon pretence of miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous power: nor is their diligence
leſſe in other means, which they vſe by daily ſollicitations for their
owne aduantage; 
<note place="margin">Prieſts haue their Agents.</note>euery
Prieſt of action,<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3148:40"/>and any ability, hauing two
Aſſiſtants aſſign'd vnto him: whoſe office, like the Familiars of
the Inquiſition, is to ſtraggle abroad, for the brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging-in of game.
Theſe ſubſeruient procurers are <hi>Laicks,</hi> and though not able to
maintaine Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, yet pry in
by-corners, nay, and put forward in open places, to ſhake and try any weake
wauering Proteſtants; and if they can get but to intertaine conference, and
giue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are to their boaſts and
inſinuations, then they bring them to be better hammered vpon the Anuill of
their great Maſters. Sometime they deale with tender game, ſcarce yet
fledge, I meane, young Youths, whom they inueigle, to tranſport to the
neſts of their Seminaries. I haue giuen you ſome examples before, and could
afford you more. If at the Schooles o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Weſtminſter, Pauls, Wincheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Eaton,
Chriſt-Church</hi> or <hi>Suttons Hoſpitall,</hi> there chance bee ſome
young man diſcontented, for the loſſe of a place in the Vniuerſitie hee
ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for; or in the Vniuerſities, ſome young graduate, halfe diſtracted
or diſcouraged, vpon the loſſe of ſome fellowſhip, or other promotion
hee aſpired vnto; Oh then there is matter to work on; none of theſe, I
warrant you, ſhall eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape without promiſe of better preferment; there
needs not one to informe them, what prouiſion is made beyond the Seas at
Saint <hi>Omers, Doway, Lisbon, Louaine, Spaine, Rome,</hi> for all ſuch
<hi>Nouices;</hi> what beautifull Colledges, ſtately Edifices, large
Reuenewes thereunto <pb n="70" facs="tcp:3148:41"/>annexed; what great liberty, what good
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, what practice of Piety.</p>
            <q> 
               <l>Fiſtula dulcè canit, volucrem dum decipit
auceps.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Like the Fowler, they can allure with diuers theſe pleaſing
notes, to tempt to their lure, and bring the Foot within the <hi>Snare: ſed
terminu siſtius gaudij, mors eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note> the
end of this prooues the moſt deadly &amp; dangerous. Some of their ſcouts
haue I known about the vniuerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> as one <hi>Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
Ford, Maſon;</hi> and diuers others could I point, at this preſent, heere
in <hi>London,</hi> who indeed are no leſſe perillous and pernicious then
the Prieſts themſelues. If they can finde any, for extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
pregnancie of wit, learning, parentage, friends, eſpecially
poſſeſſions, fit to ſerue their turnes, and condeſcend to their
expectations, by no meanes muſt ſuch ſcape their fingers.</p>
            <p>What other ſhifts haue the Prieſts to wreſt and wring from
their poore Diſciples, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall to maintaine their pomp and brauery?</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">How a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman of Saint <hi>Giles</hi> in
the fields neere <hi>London,</hi> was cheated by a Prieſt.</note>
               <hi>A
Gentlewoman</hi> of the pariſh of <hi>Saint Giles</hi> in the fields neere
<hi>Holborne,</hi> was of late time ſick, and beeing one that was well
inclining and warping toward the Popiſh pale or bent, ſent for a
<hi>Prieſt,</hi> a man very famous about this Towne, to come vnto her, and
aſsiſt her with his beſt comfort and counſell; who vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her
deſire, was ſoone with her: and beeing come, ſhee acquainted him, how the
caſe ſtood betweene Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God and her diſtreſſed ſoule; and
hauing laid herſelfe open vnto him, after the forme of <hi>Catholick</hi> 
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:3148:41"/>
               <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> her <hi>Ghoſtly Fa her</hi> the
<hi>Prieſt,</hi> told her, <hi>that ſhee ſhould not neede to take any
farther thought or care of her Soule, but commit all to him, his Abſolution
would bee auaileable, and by Prayer himſelfe would intercede for her.</hi>
Yet one thing farther hee muſt tel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her; <hi>that ſhee might bee more certaine of M rcy and
Indulgence, if there were ſome care had for the ſaying of ſo many
Maſſes for her after her death at the high Altar.</hi> The woman liſtned
to this, and liked it very well. Yea, but the Prieſt had not ſaid all;
<hi>Theſe Maſſes</hi> (he told her) <hi>could not be had without a round
ſumme of money.</hi> Shee demanded of the Prieſt, what the whole charges
might bee. <hi>Hee told her, About ſome thirty pounds.</hi> The poore
gentlewoman anſwered, Shee had not ſo much money in her cuſtodie; but
plate ſhee would deliuer him, ſufficient to raiſe ſuch a ſumme: and
accordingly ſhee deliuered it forthwith to his poſſeſsion; who, hauing
met with ſuch a booty, had little deſire to viſit any more his ſick
patient. The woman within a ſhort time after grew ſo weake in her body,
that ſhee was paſt ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of
recouery, and then ſent againe for her ſpirituall Doctor to come and
admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſome of his ghoſtly phyſick to her. But my Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had
taken paines enough before, and by no meanes would bee brought the ſecond
time vnto her. A good Caucat heere was, for her, and others to take heed of
ſuch cogging and inſinuating companions. It pleaſed God, this Gentlewoman
recouered; and, making good vſe of that abuſe ſhee receiued by this
Prieſt in her ſickneſſe, ſhe altered her Religion: and now, to the
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort <pb n="72" facs="tcp:3148:42"/>of diuers worthy and painfull Miniſters about
the City, ſhee is become a good Church-woman, and ſpends the moſt of her
time in Gods ſeruice, going daily vnto Sermons, and following nothing ſo
much as her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotions.</q>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Prieſts inſinuating with one Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris
<hi>Reid,</hi> and fiſhing for her eſtate.</note>In Summer 1623. A
Gentlewoman <hi>named</hi> Read, <hi>lying at that time ſick at</hi>
Bednall-greene <hi>neere</hi> London, <hi>and hauing Land of inheritance, of
aboue fiue hundred pounds,</hi> per annum, <hi>was vehemently ſet vpon by
ſome Ieſuites and Prieſts; inſomuch, that ſhee was inclineable to
referre her eſtate to their diſpoſall. Whereupon, ſome of her neere
kinne, repairing to a Doctor of Diuinitie, of good note in</hi> London,
<hi>informed him, how farre the Prieſts had wrought with her. Whereupon, hee
by conference and inſtruction, did ſet her right againe</hi> (as by Gods
bleſſing, hee hath confirmed diuers others). <hi>It is very probable, that
the greateſt part of that eſtate ſhould haue flowne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, as
much other our Countrey goods and Riches doe, to vnderline the
Nunneries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Prieſts viſiting M. <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlam,</hi>
to get from him his Land.</note>In <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, one
<hi>Musket</hi> a Ieſuite, and another <hi>Prieſt,</hi> came to <hi>Francis
Netlam,</hi> lying very ſick in M. <hi>Dawſons</hi> houſe in
<hi>Fetter-Lane;</hi> and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of ſome Lands or
poſſeſſions he had, to a round value, inquired of him, how he
diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of theſe his reuenues, and to whom he meant to leaue them after
his deceaſe. Hee acquainted them, that he had brothers &amp; ſiſters,
poore, and of his owne Religion (to weet, Papiſts) who did<pb n="73" facs="tcp:3148:42"/>expect them. But theſe inſinuating Prieſts, more regarding
themſelues then their Diſciples, dealt ſo farre with him, that hee was
content to giue his La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds to
themſelues, or whom they ſhould nominate, ſo to be at their
diſpoſing. Which gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, M. <hi>Muskets</hi> care was ſuch, that <hi>a
Will</hi> was drawne, and the Lands thereby conueyed to the Prieſts, or to
ſome other for their vſe. Therupon returning to the houſe where this
ſick Catholick lay, they requeſted the woman of the houſe (Miſtris
<hi>Dawſon,</hi> her husband not being within), to bee <hi>a Witneſſe to
the ſaid Will.</hi> But ſhee, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Contents thereof,
refuſed ſo to doe: neither would ſhee ſuffer them to goe to the ſick
mans chamber, vnleſſe their intent were better. So ſoone as her husband
came home, ſhee told him what the Prieſts would haue done. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon, her
husband intreated the <hi>Lecturer</hi> of the pariſh, and another
<hi>Miniſter,</hi> to perſwade the ſaid <hi>Francis Netlam,</hi> not to
bee ſo fooliſh and vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, as to giue his Land from his needy
brethren, to theſe cheating, coozening, and colloguing Prieſts. The ſick
man followed the counſell of theſe Miniſters, in whom hee found more
plaine dealing, then in the other his ſpirituall Fathers. And
notwithſtanding hee had beene long miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by the ſaid Romiſh Impoſtors, hee deſired to bee prayed
for (according to the forme of our Engliſh Church) in Saint
<hi>Dunſtanes</hi> in the Weſt, at their next <hi>Wedneſday Lecture:</hi>
an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> further to expreſſe his
conformity to our Church, hee<pb n="74" facs="tcp:3148:43"/>receiued the bleſſed
<hi>Sacrament</hi> with vs before his death.</p>
            <p>Hence then obſerue, how induſtrious our Prieſts are, not
onely to get Proſelyte men and women, but alſo Proſelyte Lands and
poſſeſſions: notwithſtanding all their pretended pouertie, <hi>bonus
odor lucri,</hi> they will omit no opportunitie to get what gaine they can. I
know this to be true, that in thoſe parts where I haue liued, and where are
moſt Papiſts of any part of this Kingdome; there is not a Popiſh
Gentleman in all the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, but there is a Prieſt to his Steward, and
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer of houſhold and reuenues; neither doth the Owner let, ſet, or
ſell any land, without the approbation &amp; conſent of theſe pretended
ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall guides. And that indeed is it which cauſeth Papiſts the more
to abound, for that a Land-lord led by ſuch directors, will not ſuffer any
one quietly to liue vpon his Land, but ſuch as the three-quarter Lord
Prieſt taketh to bee his holy children, and will be ready to doe him
ſeruice. A fine engine to wheele about, and ſcrue whole families and
Townes, by the pully which twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the long rope of Spiritualls reaching out
<hi>ad temporalia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another of their engines is, If an offender come to one of theſe
Prieſts to Confeſſion; as they inioyne him, for one part of his penance,
to ſay ſo many <hi>Pater-noſters,</hi> ſo many <hi>Creeds,</hi> ſo
ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Aue-maries,</hi> by ſcores euery day: ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they
impoſe on his head a pecuniary mulct,<pb n="75" facs="tcp:3148:43"/>hee muſt pay into
the hands of ſome other Prieſt 40, 30, 20, 10, 8, or 5 pounds (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the ability of the partie), to bee diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſaid Prieſt, a
iudicious man, in <hi>pios vſus.</hi> Which money once fingered, is very
iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly ſhared betwixt theſe two ſhriuing Prieſts, who
(<hi>Iudas</hi>-like) will haue no waſte, <hi>et te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentes marſupium,
tenentur àmarſupio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, that their Lampes may want no Oyle, their pockets no
weight, how doe they gripe, exact and extort from their poore Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples! If
a Shoomaker, or a Taylor, that hath nought but what hee earnes at his fingers
ends, chance to come vnder their fingers, his money is ill got, vnleſſe hee
offer to his holy Father a third or fourth part of his gaine. If a Countrey
Farmer bee ſo rich in Tenement or Land, that hee haue but two Oxen to yoke,
and three kine to milke, before the yeeres end one of the beaſts muſt bee
ſold, to buy the honeſt Prieſt a new ſuit, perhaps of ſwaggering
Sattin. Nay, I haue known a taxation ſuch, that out of a mans means worth
tenne pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> the Prieſt muſt perforce haue forty
ſhillings a yeere at leaſt. And in a great Shire, where I haue conuerſed,
there is not a man of that Religion, of 40 pounds a yeer reuenew and vpward,
but hee muſt, at his owne charge, keepe a Prieſt in his houſe: perhaps
ſome poor neighbours that are benefited hereby, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute ſome ſmall
matter toward it.</p>
            <p>Thus, while they pretend, that they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced<pb n="76" facs="tcp:3148:44"/>to creepe into priuate houſes for feare of perſecution, they carry
more dominion ouer the Family, then any Pariſh-Prieſt doth in thoſe
Countries where Popiſh Religion publikely preuaileth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Author of The .B of <hi>Londons</hi>
Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacie.</note>I ſhould haue commended M. <hi>Muskets</hi> wit, if hee could
at ſo eaſie a rate haue purchaſed M. <hi>Netlams</hi> inheritance. Sure,
it was a better plot, and his time better ſpent, then in writing and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
his book, called <hi>The Biſhop of London his Legacie.</hi> A pamphlet, that
I much wondred who could haue ſo little wit, and leſſe grace, to bee the
Author thereof, till that an incendiary brother of his<note place="margin">F.
Med.</note> (who took diſlike at it) confeſſed vnto mee; and F.
<hi>Musket</hi> himſelfe, in ſome ſort, acknowledged his paines-taking
therein. <hi>O per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frictam frontem!</hi> W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at impudence was heere ioynd with ignorance! How lewdly
did he and his <hi>Precurſor Kelliſon</hi> bely Him, who is now as glorious
a Starre in the heauens aboue,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Non comet a fuit, ſed
Stella.</hi>
               </note> as He was a ſhining Lamp in the firmamenr of the Church
heer on earth! 
<note place="margin">Sophocl.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (as <hi>Sopho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> commended <hi>Philoctetes</hi>) <hi>He
fought a good fight,</hi> both in defence of the faith, and in exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gnation of Hereſies, Schiſmes and
Seditions brought-in by theſe our Aduerſaries. And as <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
ſpake of <hi>Cyprian, Multi erat meriti, multi pectoris, multioris, multae
virtutis:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> Hee was worthy, wiſe,
well-ſpoken, religious.</p>
            <p>Now whereas they ſeek to get Proſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tes by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heſe monſtrous forgeries and trumperies, for<pb n="77" facs="tcp:3148:44"/>my owne part, I confeſſe, that vpon the firſt view and reading
of it, I was ſomewhat mooued with wonder, &amp; withall with poſſibility
of credence; which made mee the more diligently to enquire of it; eſpecially
reading there, that the Biſhop was reconciled to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi>
by a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Prieſt there not named. I curiouſly ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched among the
Prieſts, to learne who that might be. They named to mee F.
<hi>Preſton:</hi> but <hi>him</hi> I finde to haue conſtantly diſauowed
it, on examination: and otherwiſe I found good cauſe to think, that hee
ſpake his conſcience in that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall. Then was I poſted off to F.
<hi>Palmer</hi> a Ieſuite, and that hee was the very man: but asking him very
ſeriouſly and priuately about it, hee told me, hee neuer ſaw the Biſhop
of <hi>London.</hi> And verily, if this Ieſuite did meane to equiuocate with
mee, hee had no reaſon to ſpeak doublely on that part, but rather to
auouch, that himſelfe did that deed, or knew who did it, that he might the
better hold me in belief of that narration. In fine, I found this tale to be
nothing but a comicall fiction: and on better weighing this ridiculous
ſhameleſſe pamphlet, ſo belying Integrity, ſo outfacing the open
Sunne with audacity, and ſo farre degenerating from all ſhew of verity; I
concluded, that the frame could not be ſound, which was built vpon ſuch a
rotten foundation; nor that Religion ſincer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath
ſlanderous leaſings for her daily food. As <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith in
the behalfe of the Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tians
firſt perſecuted by<pb n="78" facs="tcp:3148:45"/> 
               <hi>Nero,</hi> that hee that knewe
<hi>Nero</hi> well, might eaſily vnderſtand, <hi>non niſi grande aliquod
bonum à Nerone damnatum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. <hi>in
Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loget. cont. Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</hi>
               </note> it was like to be a good thing, which
<hi>Nero</hi> oppoſed. So when I view the ſhameleſſe ſlanders which
ſuch Iugglers lay vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that reuerend Biſhop, I muſt needs ſay, that I
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenced his memory the more, and might well think him the more conſtant
in his Religion, by their faining him to bee wauering.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">M. Anderton.</note>Yet, thus I muſt needs
teſtifie of one the moſt ſufficient &amp; ingenuous of their Prieſts,
that, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it might make ſomewhat againſt their common
cauſe, hee plainly told mee, <hi>hee was ſorry that euer any ſuch booke
ſhould bee ſuffred to come forth; for it would doe them more hurt, then any
booke they euer wrote:</hi> meaning, as I take it, that the forgerie in it was
too palpable. But I find, that the booke is ſubſcribed by publike authority
and particular commendation to it, nor will they inflict any cenſure vpon the
lewd Father of this monſtrous lie. And hence it is, that of late they haue
altered <hi>The Title,</hi> and changed the Fronti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpice into a more darke
phraſe, making it a <hi>Proſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>popeia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth Maſter <hi>Musket,</hi> who hath foure or fiue hundred (as
I haue heard him boaſt) that come to his chamber to a Sermon, feed them with
no better fare then ſuch windy, light, empty, nay noyſom exhalations? I can
then call it but, <hi>The dreamed bread of the ſluggard. They may eat, but
not bee ſatisfied.</hi> Perhaps hee may paralell this and<pb n="79" facs="tcp:3148:45"/>greater fictions out of the <hi>Golden Legend,</hi> when he preacheth
vpon any By-Saints-day.</p>
            <p>But I heare (me thinks) the noiſe of our hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<hi>Noctua's,</hi> the Prieſts &amp; Ieſuites, blind guides, and louers of
darknes more then the light, who are ſo farre from beleeuing that any
cataract or filme is on their eyes, that they are rather per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded,
themſelues are the moſt quicke-ſighted. They know and ſee a farre off,
that although, <hi>non adhuc miſerendi tempus, non adhuc exultandi dies, the
time to haue mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The wiſe words of him that wrote
The word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</note> their appointed day be not yet come, yet they
ſhall haue a time &amp; a day whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Vaevobis,</hi> wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bee to their Aduerſaries. Their beſt dayes of late
(perhaps) ſeeme to them but a leaden, or at beſt, a ſiluer age: but a
Prieſt now in London tould mee ſometime this Lent (and it hath beene the
merry tune of many more), that <hi>they ſhould ere long haue golden
daies.</hi> Many of the Ieſuites haue of late cried, <hi>Woe to England.</hi>
Their meaning is lockt vp in a miſery, and how they will explicate
themſelues, I know not. <hi>Nocte die<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuum gestant in pectore
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtem;</hi> though they ſcape
<hi>reſtem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let mee then premoniſh the ignorant, and feebler ſort
eſpecially, who are like weak and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly flies, that they take heed how
they be caught in ſuch cobwebs, wherein the chiefe thred they ſpinne, is,
that none out of their Church can be ſaued. And further, let them beware,
leſt they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praue their ingenuous diſpoſition, in tampering with tooles
that may cut their fingers, and ſo<pb n="80" facs="tcp:3148:46"/>venture into that web
of hereticall fraud, which they want ſtrength of wit to breake thorow. I
knowe, that whom nature or education hath made ſimple, hereſie will make
proud.</p>
            <p>For who more inſolent then the ignorant? Which
<hi>Eraſmus</hi> noted long agoe,<note place="margin">Eraſm. <hi>in Spong.
aduerſ.</hi> Hutten.</note> and may well bee applyed vnto many of our
Engliſh Papiſts, who when they might bee informed <hi>de vita Chriſti, et
de via Chriſtiani,</hi> they are reſolued afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand not to bee
ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>Oh the blindneſſe of vnderſtanding of thoſe that are
called Lay-Catholickes! Iuſt here were the complaint of the Prophet, <hi>My
people bee in captiuity, becauſe they bee without knowledge.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 5.13.</note> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when I begin to weigh and meditate on
the abuſes that our Kingdome in generall, and theſe weake members thereof
in particular, ſuſtaine by thoſe Hornets and Drones who flee vp and
downe, ſtinging and wounding with the wily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuation of errour,
ſucking and gathering hony in our gardens, yea, reſting vpon diuers golden
flowres; my heart begins to bleed, my bowels to yearne, and my ſoule is
plunged in much hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe. For wo is mee! Are wee not all ſonnes to one
<hi>Father?</hi> all Subiects to one <hi>King, cuius ſub vmbrâ
ſuauiter quieſcimus,</hi> we reſt vnder his ſhade, and his boughes haue
beene long diſtended for our ſecuritie? How grieuous (alas!) is it now to
him to heare, that any his children and ſeruants ſhould bee a prey to the
Harpies of <hi>Rome;</hi> that vipers ſhould eat out their ſubſtance,
&amp; diſpoile<pb n="81" facs="tcp:3148:46"/>them of the meanes of the true knowledge of
Chriſt! All theſe things, vnleſſe they keepe you ſtill muffled, you
may eaſily diſcerne. Are they not <hi>Lords,</hi> not onely ouer your
faith, but alſo <hi>your inheritance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.</note>
although, according to the rule of their Canoniſt, <hi>Praelatio
eccleſiastica ministerium habet, non dominium:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Linwood. The Prieſts and Ieſuites in their bookes pretend that
they are ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to thoſe ouer whom in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they lord it.</note> Their
office binds them (nay, the Ieſuites vow ties them) to <hi>Seruice,</hi>
rather then <hi>Dominion.</hi> How is it poſſible (mee thinks) that they
ſhould bring you to that ſeruitude as I find they doe, ſo ſubiugate
your vnderſtanding, and impriſon your wills, that if they command any
thing, <hi>quamuis adinteritum animaeet corporis,</hi> you are readie to obey
them? and doe they not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly make vaſſals and ſlaues of you?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Good-Friday cheere. A Proceſsion from
<hi>Holborne</hi> to <hi>Tiburne.</hi>
               </note>Yeſterday being
<hi>Good-friday,</hi> this preſent yeere 1624. they made ſome of you in the
Morning, before day, goe in <hi>Proceſsion</hi> to <hi>Tiburne,</hi> in
peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiall manner; the forme of which is, for a man to <hi>walke naked from
the girdle vp ward, and ſcourge himſelf with a whip.</hi> The ſame day
twelue-month laſt paſt, at a place of your ſolemne meeting in London, you
made one whip himſelf ſo long, till he ſwouned, and was thought to bee
paſt hope of recouery, ſo that hot water was inſtantly fetched to reuiue
him. At <hi>Bruxels</hi> (as a Prieſt told mee, ſaying hee ſaw it, and
boaſting of the meritorious work) a woman, about a yeere ſince, ſo
cruelly ſcourged her ſelfe, that ſhee died of it. Is this Mortification,
to murther our ſelues, leſt ſinne murther vs, to aboliſh our life in
the <pb n="82" facs="tcp:3148:47"/>fleſh, leſt wee ſhould <hi>liue after the
fleſh?</hi> I am no enemy vnto auſterity of life, and taming or
chaſtening our <hi>bodily ſinfull members,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom.
5.</note> to bring them in ſubiection to the ſpirit, to abate the
<hi>luſts of the eye, and pride of life,</hi> to depoſe the <hi>Tyrant
ſinne from his dominion:</hi> whatſoeuer tendeth this way, for the better
whetting of our members <hi>to become weapons of righteouſnes,</hi> I wiſh
were more, rather then leſſe vſed in our reformed Churches; ſo it bee
without the opinion of merit, without pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like oſtentation, without
exceſſe, and vnnaturall hating and diſabling our corporal faculties. Such
kind of enormous flagellant <hi>Tragedies,</hi> proue ſometime as abſurd
remedies againſt ſinne, as a Philoſopher did bring againſt ſicknes;
who vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting his diſeaſed friend, that complained of the
irkſomneſſe of his diſeaſe, and deſired his aduice for curing the
ſame, or eaſing his paine, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from him, and ſhortly came againe,
and told him, hee had brought a medicine to cure all his diſeaſes, and rid
him of paine. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient hearing that welcome word, promiſed hee would take
the medicine. To whom preſently this Kil-cow Phyſicion ſhewed vnder the
lap of his coate a ſhort ſword, which would make ſhort worke. To ſay no
more of this outrageous deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: as it is <hi>Baalaiticall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Like <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts, who did lance their ſides,
&amp;c.</note> wee cannot, vnleſſe wee winke, but ſee it is alſo
<hi>Phariſaicall.</hi> If bitter chaſtiſement in this caſe be
requiſite, why ſhould it not bee performed as priuately, as our Sauiour
inioyneth 
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note>
               <hi>ſecret prayer in the Clozet,
the doore ſhut,<pb n="83" facs="tcp:3148:47"/>&amp;c?</hi> Muſt this be done before
hundreds of ſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatours? Yes verily, elſe the price of the
ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the glory of the merit, the ouer-weight of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererogation,
would be made lighter by many an ounce. And indeed, as in this, ſo in all the
reſt of the whole pageant of Popery, euery thing muſt bee theatricall
<hi>ad pompam,</hi> elſe the gazing Vulgar would not be ſo frequently and
eaſily caught.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, if ſuch inioyned penances muſt be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in an
ambling faſhion, with rouing abroad, would no other place ſerue to gad
vnto, but <hi>Tiburne?</hi> Is no other place in <hi>England</hi> left ſacred
and vnpolluted? Oh, but there is more vertue in the goale they runne vnto, then
in the race they vndertake. It was antient, to viſit <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morias
Martyrum;</hi> and ſo, the ſending of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to viſit
<hi>Tiburne,</hi> maketh a deep impreſſion in their mindes, of the
Saint-ſhip of ſome that haue there paid their debt to our Lawes. Wee know,
<hi>Martyr</hi> and <hi>Perſecutor</hi> are <hi>Correlatiues:</hi> and ſo,
in this action of pretended humiliation, there is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended an increaſe of
the Romaniſts hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Church and State of <hi>England,</hi> as
perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting, and guilty of the bloud of thoſe whom they adore. Thus euery
ſtep in ſuch pilgrimage, makes thoſe Penitents to walke further from vs:
nay, in euery ſtripe voluntarily receiued in that Iourney, the Confeſſor
that inioyned this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, thinkes hee ſcourgeth the
Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:3148:48"/>Deare Country-men, let mee, in the ſpirit of
meekneſſe, &amp; out of the tenderneſſe of my heart and affection
inlarged toward you, a little intreat you to conſider, how you are hood-winkt
and diſguiſed. Doe yet, at laſt, lay your hands on your hearts, and loath
theſe deſpicable Impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, returning vnto the truth, and aſſuring
your ſelues, that neuer any true Religion did aſſiſt and credit it
ſelfe by ſuch iuggling ſhifts, tricks and deuices, as the Ieſuiticall
brood are obſerued daily to practiſe, and many of which (I am ſure) they
ſhame to heare of.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Periury of <hi>Tho Cornford</hi>
Ieſuite.</note>For example: Bluſh they not at this; that, one <hi>Thomas
Cornford</hi> a brother of theirs, examined before my Lords <hi>Grace</hi> of
<hi>Canterbury, Iune</hi> 25. 1612. <hi>did firſt giue vnto himſelfe, the
name of Iohn Vnderwood,</hi> and ſo ſubſcribed it; <hi>affirming that hee
was a married man, and that hee had married the daughter of one</hi> Robinſon
<hi>in</hi> Irkinburge, <hi>where his wife at the time of his Examination
remained? Hee added alſo, he had beene married vnto her twelue yeers, and
that hee had by her ſix children. Hee ſaid hee was by condition a Farmer,
and that hee came to Towne, to mooue the Lord</hi> Vaux, <hi>that himſelfe
might be Tenant to his Lordſhip, for a certaine houſe and land lying
in</hi> Irkinburge, <hi>where his wife,</hi> Robinſons <hi>daughter,
remained.</hi> But this fellow, after, vpon ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morce of conſcience, or
fearing leſt his condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and eſtate might by ſome other meanes bee
diſcouered, doth of himſelfe offer to manifeſt vnto his <hi>Grace,</hi>
his condition and profeſſion; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<pb n="85" facs="tcp:3148:48"/>which, as it were on
a ſecond examination, he is admitted; and then acknowledged, <hi>That for the
ſpace of ſix yeeres, hee was brought vp in the Colledge of</hi> Rome;
<hi>and that there hee took the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Prieſt-hood, according to the
manner of that Church; and that from thence, ſome 12 yeeres ſince, hee was
ſent by miſsion into</hi> England, <hi>where by F.</hi> Garnet <hi>hee was
admitted into the Society of Ieſus: hee acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth alſo, that his name
was</hi> Tho. Cornford, <hi>and ſo ſubſcribed the ſame the ſecond
time, after that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee had ſubſigned by the name of</hi> Iohn
Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood.</p>
            <p>Will you vnderſtand how this ingenuous Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite did conciliate
ſuch contrary ſayings of his? Thus hee performed his part: 
<note place="margin">Excellent equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation.</note>Whereas he
affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med himſelfe to bee <hi>a married man,</hi> his meaning was, that his
wife was his <hi>Breuiarie,</hi> and that hee had beene married vnto it 12.
yeeres: as for <hi>his children had by</hi> Robinſons <hi>daughter,</hi>
thoſe were his ghoſtly and ſpirituall children. The reaſon why hee
called himſelfe <hi>a Farmer,</hi> was, becauſe hee was ſo to God,
according to that Text, <hi>Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de rationem villicationis tuae: Giue an account
of thy Farmer-ſhip.</hi> The reaſon why hee ſaid, <hi>hee came to take a
Farme of the L.</hi> Vaux, was, becauſe hee was ready to doe him any
ſeruice for the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all tilling of his ſoule.</p>
            <p>Read D. <hi>Sheldons</hi> book of the <hi>Miracles of
An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist,</hi> page 28. where you may read of another holy brother of the
<hi>Ignatian ſociety,</hi> who did in the ſame ſort wilfully p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ure himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:3148:49"/>Thus much for my preſent occaſion, by way
of declaration, what wholeſome vſe (by Gods grace) I haue made of the
noxious and balefull weeds that grow in the Papall garden; whereof, through my
owne vanity and leuity, hauing ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſome taſte, it hath pleaſed God to
turn thoſe poyſons into an Antidote, happy for my ſelfe, and (as I hope)
not vnfruitfull for others.</p>
            <p>But firſt, I am not ignorant, that ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars related
by mee, are like to procure mee the hatred, and perhaps, ſome malicious
machinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe that thought to hold me in perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall captiuity. But
I proteſt to God, that as I haue in ſincerity of heart, without malicious
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting, or adding any thing, giuen account of thoſe paſſages that
came to my knowledge: ſo I doe not hate the perſon of any of thoſe, who
haue pretended to haue beene my Inſtructers while I remained with them; but
wiſh to them, as vnto my owne ſoule, a ſight of thoſe corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
&amp; errours, wherein they are deepely dyed, and whereof they did caſt
ſome tincture vpon me; &amp; alſo an acknowledgement of Gods Truth
reſplendent in the Scriptures, a forſaking and abominating of that
pernicious trade, of beeing Factors and Brokers for the Papacie: The
ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions and tyrannies whereof, I maruaile, if they ſee not; and I
much more mourn, if, ſeeing &amp; inwardly acknowledging, yet they ſhould
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine and practiſe, for the keeping the poore Lay-people in awe, which
I take to bee one of<pb n="87" facs="tcp:3148:49"/>the chiefeſt <hi>Arcana Imperij,</hi>
ſecrets of State, for the maintenance of their religion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I hold my ſelfe bound in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, vpon the
ſight of mine owne error, and conſideration of the ſcandall which I haue
iuſtly giuen, to make publick proteſtation of my reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery, with vnfained
and hnmble ſubmiſſion vnto our reuerend Mother the <hi>Church of
England</hi> (the moſt orthodox and pure Church now extant in the world, and
moſt ſuitable vnto the Apoſtolick and Primitiue times, both for faith and
diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline). Before her feet I proſtrate my ſelfe with deepe ſorrow of
heart, that I haue through raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of heart, diſcontent, or any other
miſ-gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding paſſion, played the run-away out of her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily and
obedience. Wherein my fault is farre the greater, foraſmuch as I, by that
calling which ſhee hath vouchſafed mee (although vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy) in her family,
ought to haue beene a guid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vnto
others, <hi>to keepe their feet in the waies of Truth and Peace.</hi> I implore
her motherly indulgence, to open her lap to mee, her wandring returning childe,
and to vouchſafe mee ſuch pardon and abſolution, as the power of the
<hi>Keyes</hi> which ſhe hath receiued from our Sauiour, doth afford and
extend vnto penitent Delinquents. Nor did I think it ſufficient, to doe this
by a ſimple profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the cure of my vnderſtanding; but I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
held it neceſſary for mee to adde a manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch particular
meanes as I beſt knew to bee vſed by our aduerſaries, as ſtratagems to
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege<pb n="88" facs="tcp:3148:50"/>vs, and ſnares to intrap vs. Whereupon it may
perhaps pleaſe ſome to whom that care be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth, to make vſe euen of
theſe ſlender infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, for the preuenting of future miſchiefs in
that kinde, now growne very farre againſt the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, it behooued me not to be forgetfull of the bond of
nature, and of that duty which I owe to my aged Father, a Miniſter in the
Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of <hi>Exon.</hi> whoſe righteous ſoule hath been vexed with
my infamous deuiation; whoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly care and paines toward mee, euen then
when I moſt forgot him, and my ſelfe, hath not beene wanting in his writing
to me diuers Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Argument and exhortation: which, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with other
meanes, concurring with Gods mercy, haue beene the loud Calls that haue
pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced my eares, and made mee look back, and withdraw my foot <hi>out of the
horrible mire and clay</hi> wherein I ſtuck. Euen of him, whom aboue others I
haue deepely offended, I humbly craue fatherly pardon and bleſſing, not
onely ſecretly in my heart, but more publikely and authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically thus vnder
my hand.</p>
            <p>What a great debt lyeth vpon mee, not onely in regard of my
firſt beeing; my education eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in learning, and fitting mee for the
Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, by his care and coſt, but alſo for the repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that
diſcontent which hee hath iuſtly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at my obliquity! All that I can
promiſe and vowe, with the aſſiſtance of Gods grace, is, that I 
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:3148:50"/>hope to pay double in future comforts, for that which I
haue run arrerage by procuring fatherly ſorrowes. <hi>Faxit Deus.</hi>
Laſtly, to touch again on that ſtring which before I haue ſtruck, but
neuer can ſound too oft: This ſtreaming of my pen from the fountaine of my
heart, runs that courſe, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all things elſe ought to tend, euen into
the Ocean of Gods glory exalted by his <hi>Mercy,</hi> in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching out his
helping hand to ſuch miſerable creatures as my ſelf, intangled in danger,
&amp; ready to tumble into perdition. To his glorious name I offer vp my
ſelf, my ſoule &amp; body, as a liuely <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſacrifice,</hi>
vowing to bend al my faculties &amp; future indeuours, to the publiſhing of
his <hi>Truth,</hi> &amp; to the ſetting forward, by word, and by exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
that orthodox faith, and Church, which I haue wickedly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temn'd. And in
ſpecial, I make oblation of my particular thankſgiuing, as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated
<hi>Morning and Euening Sacrifice,</hi> for the dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deliuerance
vouchſafed mee; the one <hi>Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,</hi> &amp; concerning this life;
which in me, beyond expectation and naturall reaſon, was prolonged, when I
was ſaued, <hi>tanquam torris erutus e flamma,</hi> I meane, in that generall
and wofull downfall at the <hi>Blackfryers,</hi> wherein many leſſe
ſinners then my ſelfe breathed their laſt. The other deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is
ſpirituall, beeing in ſome ſort a child of that mother, as proceeding
from the due cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the other; I meane, the looſing of my bands, the
vnfettering of my heart &amp; ſoule from the <hi>Babylonian</hi> captiuity,
the diſpelling of that<pb n="90" facs="tcp:3148:51"/>cloud of Romiſh errors, which
obſcu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, though not wholy
extinguiſhed the light of Gods Truth in me. There were (I know) that ſaid
vnto mee, 
<note place="margin">Pſal. 41 8.</note>
               <hi>An euill diſeaſe
cleaueth faſt vnto him: and now that hee lyeth, he ſhall riſe no more.
But thou (O Lord) haſt put a new ſong into my mouth: Thoſe that ſit yet
in darkneſſe, ſhall ſee it, and feare: For, The Snare is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and I
am deliuered. Lord, eſtabliſh me in thy Truth: thy Word is Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="list_of_books_distributed_by_priests_in_England">
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:3148:51"/>
            <head>A CATALOGVE OR Note of ſuch Engliſh bookes (to the
knowledge of which I could come) as haue been printed, reprinted, or
diſperſed by the Prieſts and their Agents in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, within
theſe two yeers laſt paſt, or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>INprimis,</hi> the DOVVAY BIBLES, that is, the old
Teſtament onely in two Volumes, with Notes, reuiſed by D.
<hi>Worthington,</hi> and reprinted heer in <hi>London:</hi> ſold for forty
ſhillings, which at an ordinary price might bee afforded for tenne.</item>
               <item>THE NEVV TESTAMENT tranſlated by the <hi>Rhemiſts,</hi>
and reprinted in <hi>quarto:</hi> ſold for ſixteene or twenty ſhillings,
which might bee afforded for a Noble, or leſſe.</item>
               <item>THE SAME TESTAMENT in Engliſh, lately printed in <hi>decimo
ſexto:</hi> ſold for twelue ſhillings, which might bee well afforded for
foure.</item>
               <item>THE ANKER OF CHRISTIAN<pb n="92" facs="tcp:3148:52"/>DOCTRINE, in foure
parts, written by D. <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thington:</hi> the three laſt-parts printed in
<hi>London,</hi> and ſold by him at his Lodging in <hi>Turnbull ſtreet</hi>
for foureteen ſhillings, which might bee afforded for fiue
ſhillings.</item>
               <item>THE PROTESTANTS APOLOGIE, written by <hi>Brerely,</hi>
reprinted and ſold for ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene ſhillings, and might bee afforded for
ſix ſhillings, or leſſe.</item>
               <item>SAINT AVGVSTINES CONFESSI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONS, tranſlated by <hi>Tob.
Mathew,</hi> and ſold for ſixteene ſhillings, beeing but a little book
<hi>in oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauo,</hi> and might bee afforded for two ſhillings
ſix-pence.</item>
               <item>Two other bookes <hi>in octauo,</hi> lately written by
<hi>Tob. Mathew,</hi> and ſold very deare.</item>
               <item>THE AVTHOR AND SVESTANCE OF PROTESTANT RELIGION, written by
<hi>Smith,</hi> a Prieſt now in <hi>London,</hi> and ſold for ſix
ſhillings, and might bee afforded for twelue pence.</item>
               <item>LVTHER HIS LIFE AND DOC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRINE, a railing book, written by
<hi>Louell</hi> a Prieſt, who is at this preſent in <hi>London,</hi> ſold
for eight ſhillings, worth two ſhillings.</item>
               <item>AN ANTIDOTE AGAINST THE PE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIFEROVS WRITINGS OF ENGLISH
SECTARIES, in two parts, written by D. <hi>Norice</hi> a Prieſt, now
reſident in <hi>London,</hi> ſold for eight ſhillings, might be afforded
for foure ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:3148:52"/>THE GVIDE OF FAITH, written by the ſaid
Author, and ſold at an vnreaſonable rate.</item>
               <item>THE PSEVDO-SCRIPTVRIST, by the ſame Author, a book of
ſome twelue ſheetes of paper, and ſold for fiue ſhillings.</item>
               <item>THE CHRISTIAN VOVV, by the ſame Author, a book of ten
ſheetes of paper, and ſold for two ſhillings ſix-pence.</item>
               <item>The loud lying Pamphlet, tearmed, THE BI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHOP OF LONDONS
LEGACIE, written by <hi>Musket</hi> a Ieſuite, and reprinted with a preface
of a new diſguiſe: the book conteineth about ſixteene ſheetes: they
ſqueezed from ſome Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh buyers, ſix or ſeuen ſhillings a piece.
A deare price for a dirty lye. Yet I wiſh, they that haue any beliefe in it,
might pay dearer for it.</item>
               <item>THE SVMMARY OF CONTROVER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIES, written by D. <hi>Smith,</hi>
ſold as deare as the reſt.</item>
               <item>THE NEVV RELIGION, NO RELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GION, written by one
<hi>Floud</hi> a Prieſt now in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> ſold at a high rate, and
ſo are all the reſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</item>
               <item>THE SVM OF CHRISTIAN DOC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRINE, written in Latine by
<hi>Petrus Caniſius,</hi> and tranſlated into Engliſh by <hi>I.
Heigham</hi> a Prieſt in <hi>London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>THE TRVE CHRISTIAN CATHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LICK, by the ſame Author.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:3148:53"/>THE LIFE OF SAINT KATHARINE OF SIENNA, by
the ſame Author.</item>
               <item>THE PROTESTANTS CONSVLTATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON, a dangerous book, lately
written by an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne Author.</item>
               <item>IESVS, MARIA, IOSEPH, lately come out of the Preſſe,
Printed in <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>Simons à Carmelite</hi> now in
<hi>London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Two other Bookes, written by the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor; called, THE
WAY TO FINDE EASE, REST, AND REPOSE VNTO THE SOVLE.</item>
               <item>BELLARMINES STEPS in Engliſh.</item>
               <item>HIS ART OF DYING WELL, in <hi>octauo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>THE EXERCISE OF A CHRISTIAN LIFE, by <hi>S. B.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>THE VOCATION OF BISHOPS, by D. <hi>Champney</hi> now in
<hi>London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>THE IMAGE OF BOTH CHVRCHES, by M. <hi>Pateſon</hi> now in
<hi>London,</hi> a bitter and ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous book.</item>
               <item>THE EXPOSITION OF THE MASSE.</item>
               <item>A TREATISE OF THE REALL PRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SENCE, by <hi>Goddard</hi> a
Prieſt now in <hi>London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>THE LOVE OF THE SOVLE, Printed in <hi>London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>THE FOLLOVVERS OF CHRIST, by <hi>F. B.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>DEMANDS TO HERETICKS, in two parts, by D. <hi>Briſtow</hi>
now in <hi>London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:3148:53"/>AVRICVLAR CONFESSION.</item>
               <item>MISSALE PARVVM PRO SACER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOTIEVS.</item>
               <item>THE OFFICE OF OVR LADY, Or the PRIMER, two or three ſorts
of them lately printed.</item>
               <item>THE IVDGE, by <hi>G. M.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>THE RIGHT WAY TO GOD, by <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell</hi> an <hi>Iriſh
Monke</hi> now in London.</item>
               <item>SIXE BOOKES FVLL OF MARVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOVS PIETIE AND DEVOTION, by <hi>G.
P.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>THE APPENDIX, by Doctor <hi>Norrice.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A DEFENCE OF THE APPENDIX, written by Maſter <hi>Sweet</hi>
a Ieſuite lying in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>AN ANSVVER TO THE FISHER CATCHAT IN HIS OVVNE NET, by the
ſame Author. Theſe three laſt bookes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining but ſome ſixe
ſheetes of paper, either of them are ſold by the Authors and their Factors
for two ſhillings or halfe a crowne a piece.</item>
               <item>SOLILOQVIES, by <hi>R. T.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>THE ROSARY OF OVR LADY.</item>
               <item>MEDITATIONS VPON THE ROSARY.</item>
               <item>AN EXPOSITION OF THE ROSARY.</item>
               <item>THE MYSTERIES OF THE ROSARY.</item>
               <item>AN INTRODVCTION TO A DEVOVT<pb n="96" facs="tcp:3148:54"/>LIFE, by
<hi>I. Yorke,</hi> a Ieſuite now in London.</item>
               <item>MIRACLES NOT YET CEASED, by <hi>P. L. P.</hi> a
ſaltleſſe booke.</item>
               <item>THE KEY OF PARADISE.</item>
               <item>A HEAVENLY TREASVRY OF COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORTABLE MEDITATIONS, by
<hi>Antho. Batt,</hi> a Frier now in London.</item>
               <item>THE WORD OF COMFORT, written vpon occaſion of the fall of
the houſe at the <hi>Black-Friers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>THE VNCASING OF HERESIE, by <hi>O. A.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>THE TREASRY OF CHASTITY.</item>
               <item>THE WIDDOVVES GLASSE.</item>
               <item>THE ECCLESIASTICALL PROTE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STANTS HISTORY, by D.
<hi>Smith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>THE GROVNDS OF THE OLD AND NEVV RELIGION.</item>
               <item>THE HIDDEN MANNA.</item>
               <item>THE WANDRING SAINTS.</item>
               <item>THE LITTLE MEMORIALL.</item>
               <item>AN OVERTHROVV OF THE PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TESTANTS PVEPIT-BAB<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ES.</item>
               <item>THE VNITIE OF GODS CHVRCH, by one Maſter <hi>Steuens</hi> a
Ieſuite now in London.</item>
               <item>POINTERS MEDITATIONS.</item>
               <item>THE PROOFE OF PVRGATORY.</item>
               <item>A COMFORT AGAINST TRIBVLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION.</item>
               <item>LEDISME HIS CATECHISME, late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly printed heere in
<hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:3148:54"/>THE RECONCILEMENT OF THE DALMATIAN
BISHOP.</item>
               <item>THE POPES POVVER.</item>
               <item>THE LIFE OF SAINT BEDE.</item>
               <item>A TREATISE OF FREE-WILL, by Doctor <hi>Kelliſon</hi> Rector
of the Colledge at <hi>Doway</hi> and now in London.</item>
               <item>THE SACRAMENTS OF THE CA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THOLICK CHVRCH, by <hi>F. S.
P.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>DAVYES HIS CATECHISME.</item>
               <item>THE VISIBILITY OF THE CHVRCH.</item>
               <item>THE CATHOLICK GVIDE.</item>
               <item>A TREATISE AGAINST THE MARRIAGE OF PRIESTS, by
<hi>Wilſon</hi> a Ieſuite.</item>
               <item>A GAGGE OF THE NEVV GOSPEL.</item>
               <item>A SECOND GAGGE.</item>
               <item>THE HONOVR OF GOD, by <hi>Anthony Clerke.</hi> An idle frothy
booke, by a brayn-ſicke man.</item>
               <item>THE PRELATE AND THE PRINCE, a ſeditious booke.</item>
               <item>THE RVLES OF OBEDIENCE, by <hi>G. A. P.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>SAINT PETERS KEYES, by <hi>Edmund Gill,</hi>
Ieſuite.</item>
               <item>SAINT AVGVSTINES RELIGION, written by <hi>Brerely,</hi> and
reprinted.</item>
               <item>THE REFORMED PROTESTANT, by <hi>Brerely.</hi> There was a
Printing-houſe ſuppreſt about ſome three yeeres ſince in
<hi>Lancaſhire,</hi>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:3148:55"/>where all <hi>Brerely</hi> his
workes, with many other Popiſh pamphlets, were printed.</item>
               <item>THE VIRGINALL VOVV, by <hi>F. S.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>THE MIRROVR OF WOMEN.</item>
               <item>MEDITATIONS ON THE PASSION.</item>
               <item>A DIALOGVE BETVVIXT OVR SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VIOVR AND THE SAINTS.</item>
               <item>OBSERVATIONS, concerning the preſent affaires of
<hi>Holland,</hi> and the vnited Prouinces, by <hi>You knowe the
hand.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>THE INGRATITVDE OF ELIZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BETH OF ENGLAND VNTO PHILIP OF
SPAINE.</item>
               <item>THE SPIRIT OF ERROVR, by D. <hi>Smith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>MEDITATIONS ON OVR SAVI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OVRS WORDS ON THE CROSSE.</item>
               <item>EVERY SAINTS PRAYER.</item>
               <item>THE CATHOLICKS CROVVNE.</item>
               <item>THE THREE CONVERSIONS re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed, written by F.
<hi>Parſons.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>GRANADOES MEMORIALL.</item>
               <item>GRANADOES COMPENDIVM.</item>
               <item>GRANADOES MEDITATIONS, Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated.</item>
               <item>THE LIFE AND DEATH OF CAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DINALL BELLARMINE.</item>
               <item>THE SHEDDING OF TEARES.</item>
               <item>PARSONS RESOLVTIONS, reprinted <hi>Anno</hi> 1623.</item>
               <item>SIONS SONGS, or the melody of the Bleſſed.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:3148:55"/>THE DAILY PRACTICE.</item>
               <item>THE ENEMIES OF GOD, by M. <hi>Barlow</hi> a Prieſt now in
London.</item>
               <item>THE HOLY TRIVMPH.</item>
               <item>THE PROSPERITY OF THE VISI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE CHVRCH.</item>
               <item>THE MANVALL OF PRAYERS, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed.</item>
               <item>A WATCH VVORD, by F. <hi>Baker.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>THE APOLOGIST, by <hi>Richard Conway.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A TREATISE OF THE INVOCA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION AND ADORATION OF SAINTS, by
<hi>Thomas Lee.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>THE PRINCIPLES OF CATHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LICKE RELIGION, by <hi>Richard
Stanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>OF THE CONVERSION OF NATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONS, of the Miracles, of the
Martyrdomes, and of the vnion of the members of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, by
<hi>George Allanſon</hi> leſuite.</item>
               <item>A TREATISE OF TRVE ZEALE.</item>
               <item>F. DRVRY HIS RELIQVES, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what found in his ſtudy after
his death.</item>
               <item>FLAGELLVM DEI, or <hi>A Sword for Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictors:</hi> a
ridiculous pamphlet written by <hi>P. D. M.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>COFFIN, againſt D. HALL his booke, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled <hi>The
Honour of the married Clergie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>WALSINGHAM<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> HIS SEARCH, in <hi>quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>WALPOOLE, againſt Doctor <hi>Downham,</hi> of
<hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3148:56"/>FOX HIS CALENDAR, reprinted <hi>Anno</hi>
1623.</item>
               <item>FITZ-HERBERT, of Policy and Religion, reprinted.</item>
               <item>TREATISE OF FAITH, by F. <hi>Percy.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p> 
               <table>
                  <head>Faults eſcaped.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Page 3. a bloody
cataſtrophe.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>dele.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>18. Hell,</cell>
                     <cell>Rome.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>21. 40 yeeres</cell>
                     <cell>12 yeares.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>35. poyſon</cell>
                     <cell>foiſon.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>39.
<hi>Aeſculap.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cybele.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>52. blood</cell>
                     <cell>bled</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>42.</cell>
                     <cell>43.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>44 a lye</cell>
                     <cell>a lowd-ringing lye.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>44 <hi>Seth.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Aleph.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>45 bare apparell.</cell>
                     <cell>bare neck.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>44. 45.</cell>
                     <cell>54. 55.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>46. Sword of Iuſtice.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>dele.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>47. one</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>dele.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>48. Hell,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Auernus.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>55 who,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>dele.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>57. his,</cell>
                     <cell>their.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>62. found</cell>
                     <cell>fond.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>70. one,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>dele.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>87. of heart,</cell>
                     <cell>of youth.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>29. <hi>marg.</hi> ſpeaking,</cell>
                     <cell>atheiſticall
ſcoffing.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>81.</cell>
                     <cell>Two lines left out: the words
are, This my ſelfe did then ſee, together with two or three hundreth more,
preſent at that meeting.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>67
<hi>Norwich.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>North-witch.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>32. <hi>In marg.</hi> F. M.</cell>
                     <cell>F.
<hi>Me.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>76. <hi>In marg.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>omitted, This reuerend
Biſhops moſt pious and conſtant departure, was related by his worthy
ſonne at <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe: againſt the ſincere Truth whereof, I
doe not heare that any of thoſe dogs can bark.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_Catholic_priests_and_Jesuits_resident_in_London">
            <pb facs="tcp:3148:56"/>
            <head>THE NAMES OF THE Romiſh Prieſts and Ieſuites now
reſident about the City of London, March 26. 1624.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>LD Father <hi>Biſhop,</hi> the nominall Biſhop of
<hi>Chalcedon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Ouerton,</hi> his principall Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine.</item>
               <item>D. <hi>Kelliſon,</hi> Rector of the Engliſh Colledge at
<hi>Doway.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>D. <hi>Worthington,</hi> the Tranſlator or Corrector of the
<hi>Doway Bibles,</hi> and Author of the <hi>Anker of Christian
doctrine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>D. <hi>Collington,</hi> the titular Arch-deacon of London,
lodging in Saint <hi>Iones.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>D. <hi>Wright,</hi> a graue antient man, Treaſurer for the
Prieſts, &amp; very rich, thought to be worth thouſands of pounds: hee
lodgeth in the <hi>White-Friers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3148:57"/>D. <hi>Norice,</hi> one that hath written diuers
bookes of late, mentioned in the former Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue.</item>
               <item>D. <hi>Smith ſenior,</hi> ſometimes of the Colledge of
<hi>Rome,</hi> and Author of diuers peſtilent bookes.</item>
               <item>D. <hi>Smith iunior,</hi> Author of diuers other bookes no
leſſe dangerous.</item>
               <item>D. <hi>Champney,</hi> Author of the booke called, <hi>The
Vocation of Biſhops.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>D. <hi>Briſtow,</hi> ſometimes of the Colledge at
<hi>Doway.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Blackfen</hi> a Ieſuite, an ancient man, lodging in
<hi>Drury-Lane.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Sweet,</hi> a Ieſuite well knowne, lodging at the
vpper end of <hi>Holborn.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Musket</hi> a Ieſuite, lodging ouer-againſt S.
<hi>Andrewes</hi> Church in <hi>Holborn,</hi> a frequent prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, and one
that hath much concourſe of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to his chamber.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Fiſher</hi> a notorious Ieſuite, lodging neere the
<hi>Sauoy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Haruy,</hi> a very dangerous Ieſuite.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Austin,</hi> a Ieſuite, an aged man.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Boulton,</hi> a Ieſuite, lodging in Saint
<hi>Iones.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Macham,</hi> a Ieſuite, lodging neere the
<hi>Cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome-houſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Barlow,</hi> a Ieſuite, lodging about the
<hi>Cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome-houſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Townſend,</hi> a Ieſuite, a little black fellow,
very compt and gallant, lodging about the midſt of <hi>Drury-Lane</hi>
acquainted with collapſed Ladies.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3148:57"/>F. <hi>Browne,</hi> a Ieſuite, lodging in
Saint <hi>Martins Lane.</hi>
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <list>
                     <item>F. <hi>Palmer</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>F. <hi>Palmer</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> both Ieſuites, lodging about <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi>
very rich in apparell: the one vſeth to weare a ſcarlet cloake ouer a
crimſin Sattin ſuit.</item>
               <item> 
                  <list>
                     <item>F. <hi>Riuers.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>F. <hi>Riuers.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> both Ieſuites.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Lathom</hi> a Ieſuite.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Goddard</hi> a Ieſuit, lodging about
<hi>White-Fryers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Pateſon</hi> a Ieſuite, lodging in
<hi>Fetter-Lane.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Hammerſhed,</hi> lodging in
<hi>White-Fryers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Armeſtrong</hi> a Ieſuite, one that inſinuateth
dangerouſly, and hath ſeduced many.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Floud</hi> a Ieſuite, lying about
<hi>Fleet-Lane.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Floud</hi> a ſecular Prieſt, lodging in the
<hi>Strand.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Kerkam</hi> a Ieſuite.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Anderton</hi> a Ieſuite.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Moore</hi> a Ieſuite.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Moore</hi> a ſecular Prieſt.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Skinner</hi> a Ieſuite.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Simons</hi> a Carmelite, Author of diuers late
fooliſh Pamphlets: his lodging is in the lower end of
<hi>Holborne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Low</hi> a Ieſuite.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Simons</hi> next neighbour.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Knox</hi> a ſecular Prieſt.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Shellay</hi> a ſecular Prieſt.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Price,</hi> a ſecular Prieſt, who was long a
pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner in <hi>New-gate.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3148:58"/>F. <hi>Wilſon</hi> lodging about
<hi>Bloomisbury,</hi> and one that eſcaped at the
<hi>Black-Fryers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Hilton</hi> a ſecular Prieſt, one that eſcaped
the ſame time.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Medcalfe,</hi> now lodging in <hi>Shoo-Lane,</hi> a
good companion, but not guilty of much learning. He is often deepe loden with
liquor.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Richardſon</hi> a Benedictan Fryer, of great
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance about the Towne: he lodgeth at the farther end of
<hi>Grayes-Inne-Lane.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Root</hi> a ſecular Prieſt.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Hunt</hi> a Carthuſian Fryer, lodging in
<hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne,</hi> an old man.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Conway</hi> a Ieſuite.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Steuens</hi> a little man, a Monk.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Wilde</hi> a ſecular Prieſt.</item>
               <item> 
                  <list>
                     <item>F. <hi>Smith.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>F. <hi>Smith.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> two ſecular Prieſts, beſides the two Ieſuites of
that name, now reſident in <hi>London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Greene</hi> lodging ouer againſt
<hi>North-hampton</hi> Stables.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Houghton</hi> a ſecular Prieſt.</item>
               <item> 
                  <list>
                     <item>F. <hi>Southworth.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>F. <hi>Southworth.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> both ſecular Prieſts.</item>
               <item> 
                  <list>
                     <item>F. <hi>Edmunds.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>F. <hi>Edmunds.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> the one, as I haue heard, a Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite; the other, a
Franciſcan Frier.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Melling</hi> a ſecular Prieſt, lodging in
<hi>Holborne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Louell</hi> a ſecular Prieſt, lodging in
<hi>Holborne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Townely</hi> a ſecular Prieſt, lodging about the
<hi>Strand.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3148:58"/>F. <hi>Maxfield</hi> a ſecular Prieſt,
lodging in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Simon Maxfield</hi> a Deacon, lodging in
<hi>Fleet-Street.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Gerard</hi> a ſecular Prieſt, lodging about
<hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Dauyes</hi> an old blind man, lodging about
<hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne Conduit.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Bently,</hi> I know not of what order.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Purſell</hi> an Iriſh man, a Monk, a young proud
fellow.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Walſingham,</hi> lodging<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> about the
<hi>Cuſtome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Linch,</hi> an Iriſh man.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Gerald,</hi> an Iriſh man.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> an Iriſh man.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Stannihurſt,</hi> an Iriſh man.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Carrig,</hi> an Iriſh man.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Houling,</hi> an Iriſh man.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Chamberlaine</hi> a ſecular Prieſt, lodging about
the <hi>Black-Friers,</hi> a man of great imployment.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Turpin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Annieur</hi> a French-man.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſtle.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Iones,</hi> alias, <hi>Hay,</hi> a Ieſuite.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Iones</hi> a ſecular Prieſt.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Martin</hi> a Monk, a Citizens ſonne of
<hi>London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Baſtin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Wood,</hi> a very dangerous fellow.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Bellingam.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Young.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3148:59"/>F. <hi>Harris.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Baldwin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Conniers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Yorke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Brookes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Arncot.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Hughes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Scroope.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Langtree.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Vmpton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Bold,</hi> a Benedictan Monk.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> a Ieſuite.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Line.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Doughty.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Read.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Chambers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Halſal.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>North.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Cox,</hi> a Ieſuite.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>Baniſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Eueleigh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Powell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Skinner.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Edwards.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>F.</hi> Io. Worthington.</item>
               <item>F. <hi>White.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Stroud.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Iennings.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Bat.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Sanders.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Dier.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3148:59"/>F. <hi>Heigham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Rimmington.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Molineux.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Birket.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Kinſman.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Durham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Two Prieſts,</hi> lodging in Miſtris <hi>Fowlers</hi>
houſe in <hi>Fetter-Lane,</hi> whoſe names I cannot learne.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe bee all the birds of this feather, which haue come to my
eye or knowledge, as reſiding in or reſorting to this City: yet aboue
ſeuen times ſo many there are, that ouerſpred our thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets through
<hi>England,</hi> as appeareth by the empty neſts beyond the Seas, from
whence they haue flowne by ſhoales of late; I meane, the Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
Colledges, which haue deepely diſgorged by ſeuerall Miſſions of them,
and alſo by particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar computation of their diuided troops; when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in one
Shire where I haue abode ſometime, there are reputed to neſtle almoſt
three hundred of this brood.</p>
            <p>Though they bee heere ſet downe by one name, they are not
vnfurniſhed of diuers other names, which they change at pleaſure.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
